■
本電影由 悠悠電影 原創壓製
www.YoYozz.com
■
根據真實事件改編
Based on a true story.
不懂的事情，你自然會多加小心
It ain't what you don't know that gets you into trouble.
惹禍上身的是你自以為懂的事 -馬克吐溫
It's what you know for sure that just ain't so.
（淹死的都是會水的）
Mark Twain
弗蘭克，老婆孩子還好吧？
Hi ya Frank, how are the wife and kids?
你考慮過買國庫券或事業公司股票嗎？抽煙嗎
you know, shouldn't y'all be considering treasury bonds or utility stocks? Smoke?
在70年代後期
in the late seventies
銀行業並不是賺大錢的行業
banking wasn't a job you went into to make large sums of money.
絕對廢柴行業！
It was a fucking snooze!
到處是窮鬼！
Filled with losers!
都是來賣保險，做帳的
Like selling insurance, or.... accounting
如果銀行業廢柴的話
And if banking was boring...
證券部門就是植物人呆的地方
then the bond department at the bank was straight up comatose.
大夥都知道證券是怎麼回事
We all know about bonds....
把證券當禮物送給你的15歲小屁孩
You give em to your snot nosed kid when he turns fifteen
到他30了，能拿到一百來塊錢
Maybe when he's thirty he makes a hundred bucks.
累不累啊？
Boring!
千呼萬喚，所羅門兄弟公司的劉易斯駕臨
That is until Lewis Rainieri came on the scene at Salomon Brothers
這名不經傳的人物，對你的影響…
You might not know who he is
比起喬丹、iPod、視頻網站加起來還要大！
But he changed your life more than Michael Jordan, the I-Pod and Youtube put together!
先生們，咱們一起發財吧！怎麼樣？
Hey Gentlemen, let's get some money in here. Let's make some money! What do you say?!
可能當時劉易斯還不知道 但其實他已經改變了歷史
You see, Lewis didn't know it yet, but he already changed banking forever
就用最簡單的這個點子
with one simple idea.
房貸證券(MBS)
The mortgage backed security.
或者私營房貸證券
or... Private Label MBS
你們都背著普通的房貸
You got your average persons mortgage
固定利率，30年還清，沒意思！ 定額小筆錢償還，就這樣了
fixed rate, thirty years, boring! Same, small payoff. Right!
但是…
But......
如果你把上千個房貸打包起來
when you add thousands of them all bundled together
忽然回報率上升了，但風險還很小
suddenly, the yield goes up, but the risk is still small, because....
因為它們是房貸，哪個神經病不還房貸呢？
Well, they're mortgages, and who the hell doesn't pay their mortgage?
這種證券評級怎麼樣？
What exactly is the credit-rating on this bond?
證券評級…是AAA級別！
This bond gentlemen... Is AAA-Rating!
這就是我們密西根州養老基金一直找的啊！
This is exactly what the Michigan State Pension fund has been looking for!
- 我買兩千萬！- 別掃興啊，放開點！
I'll buy twenty million! -Oh come on, live a little!
兩千五百萬！
Twenty five million!
錢就像下雨一樣來了！
The money came raining down!
銀行家破例從鄉村俱樂部跑到了脫衣舞夜總會
And for the first time, the banker went from the country-club to the strip-club.
很快，股票和存款都沒人考慮了
Pretty soon, stocks and savings were almost inconsequential.
每年大夥都買賣5百億，1千億，2千億的房貸證券
They were doing fifty, a hundred, two hundred billion in mortgage bonds
還有幾十種其他證券
and dozens of other securities a year.
1970年代末，Christie Brinkley模特演員，因泳裝封面照出名
*1970, Christie Brinkley
1980年9月22日，裡根總統對古巴裔美國人演講
*1980 Ronald Reagan
1980年6月20日，《福祿雙霸天》喜劇電影
*1980 The Blues Brothers
1984年1月24日，第一代蘋果電腦
*1984 First Mac
1986年8月20日，吉姆·貝克“傳承會”教會演講，後因其性醜聞組織破裂
*1986 Tammy Faye Messner and Jim Bakker
1980年代，世貿大廈建築群建成
*1980 World Trade Center complex
1982 巴斯奎特作品《Self Potrait As A Heel》, 1988年去世
*1982 Jean-Michel Basquiat
美國人都沒注意到金融行業已經成為領頭羊
And America barely noticed that it's number one industry became boring old banking
1986 電影《壯志凌雲》
*1986 Top Gun
1981-1989 老布什擔任總統
*1981-1989 George H. W. Bush
1980 毒品。80年代軍方加入禁毒力量。
*1980 Drugs
1989年8月19日，柏林墻倒塌
*1989 Fall of the Berlin Wall
1990 說唱歌手LL Cool J歌曲《Mama Said Knock You Out》
*1990 LL Cool J - Mama Said Knock You Out
1998年 克林頓 萊溫斯基緋聞
*1998 Monica Lewinsky and Bill Clinton
1998年8月15日 iMac G3, 第一台蘋果一體機，精簡型電腦的鼻祖。
*1998 iMac G3
2001 小布什總統上台
*2001 George Walker Bush
然後三十年後，08年的一天
And then... one day, almost thirty years later, in 2008
1995年4月19日 俄克拉何馬城爆炸案
*1995 Oklahoma City bombing
1990年代 歌手Snoop Doggy Dogg和Tupac
*1990 Snoop Doggy Dogg and Tupac
1997 《南方公園》首播
*1997 Eric Cartman in South Park
1998 谷歌公司成立
*1998 Google
1994 辣妹合唱團
*1994 Spice Girls
2000 美國LGBT同志權利運動
*2000 Rainbow flag, LGBT movement
2002 科恩《AliG個人秀》上映，也是《波拉特》主演
*2002 Da Ali G Show
一切轟然倒塌
It all came crashing down!
貝爾斯登公司陷入泥潭，美聯儲幫忙救急
Bear Stearns was in a death spiral and the FED brokered it's sale.
現代歷史上最嚴重的經濟危機
The worst financial crisis in modern times
幾十年以來最大的金融海嘯
The largest financial disaster in decades
很可能是整個時代最糟的情況了
And perhaps the end of the era
5百萬人丟了工作
5 million unemployed
到最後，劉易斯的房貸證券 異變成了摧毀全球經濟的怪物
In the end Lewis Rainier's mortgage backed security mutated into a monstrosity that collapsed the whole world economy
專家、領導人或者電視上的權威都沒能預料到
And none of the experts, or leaders, or talking heads had a clue it was coming.
*驅逐通知
*Eviction Restoration Notice
我估計你們也沒弄明白髮生了什麼事情
and I'm guessing most of you still don't really know what happened.
是啊，大家也就是人云亦云一下…
Yeah, you got a sound bite you repeat so you don't sound dumb, but come on....
(美國財政部長）我們的金融機構是強有力的！
(Henry Paulson) Our financial institutions are strong!
不過確實有人預料到這事兒發生
But there were some who saw it coming.
整個世界都在虛假狂歡 少數的局外人和怪才卻獨具慧眼
While the whole world was having a big old party, few outsiders and weirdos saw what no-one else could.
不是我，我才不怪呢，等會再跟你說我的酷事兒
Not me, I'm not a weirdo, I'm pretty fucking cool, but... we'll meet again later!
這些人發現了經濟中心的彌天大謊
These outsiders saw the giant lie at the heart of the economy
方法不難，只是隨大流的人永遠不會去做：
and they saw it by doing something the rest of the suckers never thought to do.
親自去了解
They looked
《大空頭》
The Big Short
貫穿整個20世紀30年代…
Through the nineteen thirties....
房產市場…全國性的崩潰
The housing market collapsed... nationwide.
大概80%都完了
By roughly 80 percent.
其中有一半的房貸都違約了
And half of all .. eh ... mortgage debt was in default.
那時候有…
There were.. Very......
明確的鑒別指標，相當好認
Specific identifiers. Extremely recognizable.
* 麥克·貝利，賽恩對沖基金經理
*Michael Burry
稍等，比方說
wait... for instance
狂熱的標誌之一
W-w-w-w one of the hallmarks of mania.
是快速上升的複雜性和欺詐性的利率
is that rapid rise and complexity, and the rates... they frauded
居然在上升！
Did you know.... They're going up!
我這人習慣自己呆著
I've always been.. more comfortable.. when alone.
可能是我玻璃假眼的原因吧
I believe... maybe... it's because of... my glass eye.
小時候得過病，眼睛壞了一邊
i lost the eye... in a childhood illness.
我就不再合群了
separates me from people.
…利率居然在上升！
Did you know... They're going up!
…欺詐性的利率達到了30年代最高點
Highest fraud rates since the nineteen thirties.
我還真不了解
-No, I didn't know that.
我…是說1933年
I mean.. ghe   ghe  ghe... nine ... nineteen thirty three
大蕭條的第四年
the fourth year of the great depression
兒子你表現的一直很好，教練都表揚你了
-You were playing so great son, even heard the coach say it!
我想回家
Can we just go home?
所有社交活動，都會讓我和對方不舒服
All social interf.. actions are awkward for me and for the.... person
哪怕我想誇誇別人，也詞不達意
Even when i try to compliment... it somehow... it comes out wrong....
你頭型不錯啊，你自己理的嗎？
You have a very nice haircut, you do it yourself?
哦…你說啥？
-huh, What?
不是我…嗯…
-No, i eh....
抱歉，別往心裡去
I'm sorry... please...
我老是這樣，我老婆讓我多和別人交流
I'm going on and on. My wife told me i need to share more.
聽起來挺好的建議
-That seems healthy.
那我就在這兒乾了？我覺得我能幫你籌款
So .. I get the job? I really think i could help you fund.
好啊，那太好了
Yeah.... Yeah... sure!
- 你叫？… - 大衛，太棒了
- You're -David!... David.... Great!
那我去找個位子，有什麼我能上手幫到你的工作嗎？
I guess I'll go find a desk. Is there anything you want me to work on for start?
…有
ehh..... Yeah.
你回頭找我也行！
-You could let me know later!
*賽恩資本
*Scion Capital
你…你…覺得
D... d... d... did ya... did you
你覺得當時奇怪嗎…
Think it was strange when...
那時…
Ehm...
2001年互聯網泡沫破裂的時候…
the tech-bubble burst in 2001
硅谷的房價…
And the housing market in San- Jose.
世界科技中心的房價…
Tech-Capital of the world....
卻逆勢上漲…
Went up.....
有點…不，不奇怪！
it's strange... -No, no!
這是房產…房產一直很穩定，風險也低
it's housing... housing is always stable... low-risk.
我說的就是這點很奇怪
That's the idea ... yeah.
我要你幫我找到…
I want you to get me....
賣的最火的20個房貸證券
The ... eh....Top-20 selling mortgage bonds
你想要知道最火的20家是哪些？
-So, you want to know what the top-20 selling mortgage bonds are?
不不不，我要知道每一家的所有房貸數據
No, no, no, i want to know what mortgages are in each one
* 2005年3月
* 2005 Mar
稍等稍等…這些房貸不是…
-Wha.. wait... -Aren't those mortgages made up of
這些房貸證券不是成千上萬個房貸組成的嗎？
-Wait... aren't those bonds made up of thousands and thousands of mortgages?
是啊
Yeah...
我這就去辦，貝利博士
Right away, Dr. Burry.
證券交易委員會房貸證券商
*SEC mortgage brokerage firm
盈利38% 賽恩淨值
*SCION VALUE
證券交易委員會 房貸證券商違規
*SEC mortgage brokerage firm violations
沒有找到任何匹配網頁
*did not match any documents
bgm 《Blood and Thunder》by Mastodon
*BGM ?°Blood and Thunder?± by Mastodon
我人不錯，整天樂呵呵的
a nice guy... all day long.
你去問別人，大夥都願意和我相處
hmm.. ask anyone...hmm, I'm a pleasure to work with.
可是我兒子只要辦砸了事兒
But the second my son screws up
我…
and...
我就對他吼，就像我爸對我一樣…
yelling at him... just like my dad did to me.
感覺自己控制不住自己的嘴…
You hear the words that are coming out of my mouth.
抱歉我遲到了，沒出租車！
Sorry I'm late, no cabs!
啊
Aaaahh
你們評評理
So get this....
昨天我和私人銀行的一個人聊
I met with this retail banker yesterday..
本來是讓他投資我的基金
I'm supposed to be getting him to invest in a fund,
結果我開始和他較真有關透支的問題
instead, i start drilling him about overdraft analysis
他的銀行讓客戶寫了十幾個支票
and how his bank will let customers write ten... twelve cheques
還不告訴客戶已經透支了
Before telling them they're overdrawing.
這個小人…
and this creep....
用這種卑鄙的方式賺了十億多
is making billions off screwing over people this way.
我越來越壓不住火，我問他
And I'm getting madder and madder, and i ask him.
瞪著他，質問他
I look him in the face and i say:
你晚上睡得著覺嗎？不怕鬼叫門嗎
How can you sleep at night, knowing... that you're ripping off working people.
你猜怎麼著…他扭頭走了！
And know what he did.... He left!
也不理我，直接走人
He just walks out of the lunch, doesn't say a word.
這是什麼玩意？好像我惹著他了
What the fuck is that? Who's fucked up in that scenario?
錯在我？還是這個傻逼？
Am i? Or is this douche-bag?
把我晾在那兒，誰更那個？
who leaves me hanging... Is he the fucked up one?
- 還給我臉色看！- 咱們以前說過幾次了
Trying to make me feel bad about myself! -We have talk about this numerous times
- 讓他去死吧  - 你不能遲到了就搶別人的話
Fuck him! -You can't come in late and hijack the entire session!
你說什麼啊，我沒搶啊
What do you mean, i didn't hijack the meeting.
- 我搶話了嗎？- 搶了
Did i hijack this session? -Yeah
(這是團體心理治療)
*group therapy
你幹啥的？
What do you do?
我做商品期貨的
I'm in commodities.
我等著看你的好戲！
Good luck with that!
馬克…
Marc...
我知道你剛失去了親人
I know you've suffered a terrible loss,
你想要聊聊嗎
Do you want to talk about that?
這事兒我不會開口
I don't talk about that.
稍等…
Hold on...
稍等…靠，我得接電話了，抱歉！
Hold on.. Shit.. let's take this, sorry!
對不起了！
Sorry!
伯特，你怎麼做我不管
I don't care Porter...
（馬克·鮑姆）
* Mark Baum
這傢伙賺的錢是刮人骨頭來的，能撐多久
This guy's whole business is build upon ripping people off,how long can that last?
大夥再見！
Bye everybody!
85…
85...
這個逾期30天，這個60天沒交了
That's 30 days late, that's 60 days late.
(期末余額；初始余額；損失)
*EndSchedBal, OriginalBalCalc, ActiveLoss
按時還貸
Pay on time.
這些FICO信用評分…
These Fico-scores
盈利38.0% 賽恩淨值
38.0
你們這下現原形了…
They're caught up with their pants....
30天逾期
30 days late...
貸款價值比…大概是5
Loan to Value.... maybe 5
可能是9
maybe 9
60天逾期，天哪
60 days late, jeez!
聞所未聞
I've never heard of that.
30天逾期
30 days late
他一天都沒動窩了
He hasn't move all day.
他每隔幾天都這樣一次
He does this every few days.
他雇了我以後就沒再理過我
Hasn't spoken to me since he hired me.
房貸公司本息已墊付 （這是放貸者有信心收回房貸時的做法）
*Servicer Advanced
麥克，你還好嗎
Michael, how are you guy?!
勞倫斯，我找到了有意思的東西
Lawrence, I've put out something really interesting...
麥克你幹的好，你每次找到有意思的東西 我們就能躺著賺錢了
Great Michael, whenever you find something interesting, we all sit to make money.
看上哪個股票了
What stock are you vowing?
不不不…不是股票，我要做空房地產市場
No, no , no no.. I wanna, i wanna short the housing market.
是嗎？房地產市場可是堅如磐石
Really? But the housing market is rock-solid!
格林斯潘說過，泡沫是局部現象，斷供的很少
Greenspan just said: "Bubbles are regional, defaults are rare!"
告訴他們我一會就到
Tell em I'll be there in a minute
你再說一遍
Say again!
聽好了，格林斯潘說錯了！
Look... Greenspan's wrong!
我知道你不是故意的
Look, i don't think you mean to do this, but eh..
可你有時候說話太瞧不起人
sometimes you sound very dismissive and superior.
事情本來就是這樣，格林斯潘錯了 你讓我怎麼說…
It's a fact, Greenspan's wrong. I don't know how if you want your thr....
麥克…
Look, Michael...
四年前你還是個博士，只有個破網站和一點繼承來的錢
Metro Capital backed you four years ago when you were a Doctor with a
我們全球國際資本就力挺你了
dinky web page and some inheritance money,
一直以來業績也不錯…你繼續做股票…
We've all done very well, look... Why don't you just stick with stocks....
你了解我這個人…我…我
You know me.... I, I, I, I,
我的風格就是找能賺錢的地方
I look for value, wherever it can be found.
情況就是
The fact is
這些房貸證券…
That these mortgage backed securities
裡面有相當高風險的可調利率房貸
Are filled with extremely risky sub-prime adjustable rates.
等這部分到07年左右開始發作
and when the majority of these adjustable rates kick in.... in '07
市場就會衰退
They will begin to fail
如果最終能占到15%以上 整個房貸證券市場就毫無價值
and if they fail above 15 percent the whole bond is worthless.
麥克，停下來再想想，回頭我再找你聊
-Michael, just take a beat, we'll talk about this later!
勞倫斯，別給我來這套…如果…
Lawrence please, don't patronize me, if ... it .. is...
房貸證券，次級貸，份額…
-Mortgage backed securities, sub-prime loans, tranches....
名詞讓人頭疼是吧？
Is pretty confusing right?
是不是讓你覺得智商特別低
Doesn't it make you feel bored.... or stupid....
這就是它的本意
Well... it's  supposed to.
華爾街特別愛用玄乎的詞兒，讓你覺得只有他們才能做的來
Wall-street loves to use confusing terms, to make you think only they can do what they do.
或者你撒手不管
Or even better.....
他們就更高興了
for you just to leave them the fuck alone.
我們讓演員瑪格在泡泡浴裡解釋給你聽
So... here's Margot Robbie in a bubble-bath to explain.
大概意思就是，劉易斯的房貸證券 讓大銀行瘋狂賺錢
Basically, Lewis Rainieri's mortgage bonds were amazingly profitable for the big banks.
他們從2%的買賣提成中賺了幾十億
They made billions and billions off of their 2% fee they got for selling each of these bonds
但慢慢房貸不夠用來組成證券了
But then they start ranning out of mortgages to put in them.
畢竟房子和能買房的人都是有數兒的，對吧？
After all, there are only so many homes and so many people with good enough jobs to buy them... right?
銀行就開始把風險越來越高的房貸做成證券
So the banks started filling these bonds with riskier and riskier mortgages
謝了，亨利
Thank you Hendry
這樣的話，機器就能一直轉著了
That way, they can keep that profit machine churning right?
對了，這些高風險的房貸，就叫：次級貸
By the way, these risky mortgages are called: Sub-Prime.
下回，聽到次級貸這個詞，你就想：狗屎貸
So... whenever you hear sub-prime... think: Shit
麥克老兄發現…
Our friend Michael Burry found out,
這些房貸證券
that these mortgages bonds
本來應該至少有65%的3A評級 但其實裡面就是一坨屎
that were supposedly 65 percent AAA, were actually just, basically full of shit.
所以他要做空房貸證券
So now he's going to short the bonds
也就是…賭房產市場跌
which means.... Bet against.
懂了吧？太好了
Got it?.... Good!
別看姐洗澡了！
Now fuck off!
很快人們就會發現這個機會的，咱們得快點乾
It's only a matter of time before someone else sees this investment, we have to act now.
你怎麼就知道這些證券不值錢？
How do you know the bonds are worthless?
這裡面不是有上千頁房貸嗎？
Aren't they filled with fucking thousands of pages of mortgages?
我都看了
I read them!
- 你都看了？ - 我都看了
-You read them? I read.... Yeah!
沒人這麼腦子進水，打包房貸的證券律師才不得不看
No-one reads them, only the lawyers who put them together read them!
我覺得他們也不懂紙裡包的是什麼
I don't think they even know what they've made
有這些垃圾貸款，房地產註定火不起來
The housing market is propped up on these bad loans.
定時炸彈在，我要做空房產市場
It's a time-bomb and i want to short it.
憑藉什麼做空？
Through what instrument Michael?
現在還沒有做房貸證券的保險或期權
There are no insurance-contracts or options for mortgage bonds.
這證券太穩定沒人做！
The bonds are too stable!
勞倫斯…
Lawrence....
我打算這麼幹…
This is what I'm gonna do....
我要讓銀行，專門為我做一個金融工具
I am gonna get a bank to make me one.
然後…
Then.....
我再買下來
I'm gonna buy it.
我不做這種買賣
I don't want that kind of business!
這錢不幹淨，是黑心錢
Money is not money! That's bad money!
嘿！看著點！
Hey... Excuse me!
我問你，什麼公司這麼玩弄客戶 還能做大？
Let me ask you this: What company treats its customers that shittily and succeeds?
好吧…高盛銀行…
Fine... OK... Goldman....
馬克不信任何人
Without proving it
他小的時候在猶太學院學法典時
When he was a kid he excelled at studying the Talmud and Yeshiva.
廢話少說，有天他老師對他的母親說
Whatever! But, one day his Rabbi told his mom why.
保羅不錯，馬克學習法典也成績優異
Paul is a fine boy and Mark is an excellent student of the Torah and Talmud
那還有什麼問題，老師？
Then what's the problem Rabbi?
是因為馬克努力學習的理由
It's the reason Mark is studying so hard.
他是想要找到上帝福音中的矛盾之處！
He's looking for inconsistencies in the word of God!
那他找到了嗎？
So has he found any?
以後，馬克就在華爾街成立了自己的基金
Later Baum started his own fund on Wall-street.
他對屁話可是有狗一樣嗅覺
He had an amazing nose for bullshit.
哪裡有蠢蛋在胡說，他都會給大夥指出來
He wasn't afraid to let anyone know, when and where the bull had gone number 2.
後來馬克經歷了不幸，整個世界觀都陰暗了
Then a tragedy happened to Mark and it turned his whole world really dark
開始覺得整個金融系統都是騙局
and ready to believe the whole system was a lie.
稍等
Hold on!
辛西婭找我，我20分鐘到辦公室
It's Cynthia, I'll be in the office in twenty minutes.
親愛的
Hi Honey!
咨詢師打電話給我，你怎麼又這樣了
The therapist called.... You did it again!
沒出租車有什麼辦法
There were no cabs... What was i supposed to do?
我很擔心你的狀態
I worry about you Mark!
我至少去報到了
At least i went
你這樣，像是想把全世界都理順了
You're running around like you have to right every wrong in the world.
- 好吧… - 一直氣鼓鼓的
-Ok... -How angry
你說的對！我就是心眼小，現在還生氣了！
Fine! You know what... I'm a mean guy and I'm pissed off!
可我這個圈子，留下爛攤子 擦屁股走人的太多
But... It is a shitstorm out here sweetie. You have no idea the kind of crap people are pulling.
大夥還臉上自帶拍恩雅MTV的表情
and everybody is walking around like they're in a goddamn Enya-video.
以後他們全被玩完
They're all getting screwed you know!
他們關心什麼？關心球賽！
You know what they care about? They care about the ballgame!
關心哪個女演員去戒毒了！
Or they care about what actresses went into rehab!
你得讓醫生給你開點藥了
I, I think you should try medication!
不行，咱倆商量過，影響工作的藥不能吃
No, no, we agreed, if it interfered with work.
你這麼恨華爾街，消消氣就別幹了
you hate Wall-street, but maybe it's time to quit?
- 我愛這一行！- 你恨這一行！
I love my job! -You hate your job!
- 我愛這一行！- 你都這麼鬱悶了！
I love my job! -You're miserable!
我愛我的工作，真的！
I love my job, I love my job honey!
馬克！
Mark!
想起發生的事情，我每天也心裡不舒服
I am sad every day about what happened.
你肯定也不好受，可你從來不表現出來
I know you must feel the same, but you never show it!
我知道你們兄弟倆關係很好
I knew how close you were to your brother.
卡布！
CAB!
你去哪兒了
Where'd ya go pal?
卡布！
CAB!!
每天我都覺得你想開口聊聊，可你總是忍著
Everyday i think you're gonna talk about it, and you never do!
你能試著做一點改變嗎？
Will you ever think about the idea of making a change?
好吧，親愛的，我會認真考慮的…
Fine, fine, honey, you know what, i will consider it, but honestly....
不過我真的沒事兒，放心
Cynthia I'm OK, I really am!
嘿！這是我搶來的出租
Hey, Hey! No, no, my cab!
我的出租！我的！
That's my cab, that's my cab, That is my cab!
- 蠢貨！ - 滾蛋！ - 你滾蛋！
-Schmuck! -Fuck you! -Fuck you!
我等會再打給你
I'll call you later.
我要買…房貸證券的互換
I wanna buy.... swaps on mortgage bonds
這種信用違約互換，來擔保
Credit default swap, that will pay off...
房貸證券不能兌換的情況
If the underlying.... bond fails.
- 你想要賭房價跌？ - 是的
-You want to bet against the housing market? Yes
* 高盛公司
*Goldman Sachs
為什麼？
Why?
除非有上百萬的美國人房貸斷供才有可能
Those bonds only fail if millions of Americans don't pay their mortgages.
歷史上從來沒有過這種事
That's never happened in history.
恕我直言，貝利博士 我覺得您投資不太明智
If you'll excuse me Dr. Burry, that seems like a foolish investment.
按照市場和銀行的主流預期和大眾看法
Based on... prevailing sentiment of the market and banks, and popular culture...
我這麼做是不明智
Yes, it's a foolish investment. But eh...
但是所有人都錯了…
Everyone's wrong...
呵-呵-
That's a good one.
貝利博士，華爾街是賺錢的地方 有免費的錢我們自然來者不拒
This is Wall-street Dr. Burry, if you offer us free money, we're going to take it
我唯一的顧慮是…萬一房貸市場垮了…
My one concern is, is that.. eh.. when the bonds fail..
我要確保你們賠付…
Eh... i want to be certain,
你們萬一償還能力不夠，我的錢怎麼辦
of payment, in case of solvency issues with the bank.
您不是在說笑吧
-I'm sorry, are you for real?
你想要賭房地產崩潰，還擔心我們不能賠付你？
You want to bet against the housing market, and you're worried we won't pay you?
是的，就是這意思
yes.. that's correct.
我覺得我們能做成這筆買賣
Listen.. I think we will make this work
房貸證券不可能出事的
mortgage bond is never gonna crash
現在市場還非常穩固
bacause it's so solid right now
那我們繼續和他談
getting on and deal with it
嗯
Mmhhhh.
貝利博士，我們會制定一個現收現付的賠付辦法
Dr Burry, we could work out a pay-as-we-go structure that would payout if the bonds fail.
這也意味著，如果證券勢頭上漲
It would also apply to your payments if the value of the mortgage-fund goes up
你要每個月付給我們保險費用
You'd have to pay us monthly premiums.
您能同意這樣的條款嗎，貝利博士？
Is that acceptable Dr. Burry?
很好…沒問題
Yes.. it is, Yes.
我這裡有招股說明書
Em.. I have prospectuses on,
想給你看6個房貸證券
six mortgage-backed securities i want to show you
這些多數是審批過的房貸
The majority of them are accepted mortgages.
貝利博士，這些應該沒問題！
Dr Burry, these should be fine!
我們能賣給你5百萬的房貸證券的信用違約互換
We're prepared to sell you 5 million in credit default swaps on these mortgage bonds.
能不能賣給我一億？
Can we make it a hundred million?
那也沒問題！我們能準備好一億
Absolutely! We can make it one-hundred million.
我們會聯繫你，把文書發給你
We'll be in touch, send some paperwork over.
- 我挺喜歡這杯子的，想給我兒子帶一個 - 拿走吧！好的！
I like these cups, could i take one for my son? -Have one, Yes, Yes!
謝謝！
Thank you!
拿走兩個也行！
Have two!
bgm: 《Money Maker》by Ludacris
*BGM MONEY MAKER by LUDACRIS
* “互換”像兩人對賭，如果房市上漲 那麼麥克要按月交保險費，因為銀行承擔風險
*credit default swaps
*如果房市崩潰，房貸證券無法交易 銀行賠錢給麥克
*與保險不同，互換不用真正去買被保的東西。
*credit default swaps
* 德意志銀行
*Deutsche Bank
有可能賣給我2億嗎？
Is there any way to do two-hundred million?
我們是可以…但你得想清楚了
We can... But are you sure?
當然…我們當然可以！
Absolutely... Absolutely, we can!
*國家銀行和貸款公司 *美國最大的次級房貸公司，08年被收購
*Countrywide BANKING & HOME LOANS
*美國銀行
*Bank of America
我們有各種服務，比如園藝等…
-We do, eh... different projects we do gardening, we do
有關證券，我想… （貝爾斯登公司）
the bonds.... I'd like to .. eh...
別人說你走極端也沒什麼不好的
- It's not bad for yourself to be found extreme
這樣活著才酷！
It's very cool!
*2011年布萊尼在倫敦討論自己首部電影
*2011 Britney Spears talking about Crossroads in London
*2007年 吉姆·克拉默談次級貸
*2007 Jim Cramer
好比我本來想買24盎司的T骨牛排
I ordered the 24-ounce T-bone
結果卻拿到了8盎司的碎肉
which was choice rather than the 8-ounce filet I went for volume
我想買頂級的，卻買了次級的…
rather than prime I went for subprime.. and just..
*瑞士瑞信銀行
*Credit Suisse
*我們想你了
*We miss you.
蘭德，三個月後才發獎金，你現在就這麼逍遙
Hey Randall, what with the Dom? Bonuses aren't for three months.
我們剛賣了2億的房貸證券的信用違約互換
We just sold 200 million in credit-swaps for mortgage-bonds
加利福尼亞冒出來的瘋子基金經理
Some fund-manager from California, fucking crazy right?!
老夥計，咱們就得賺傻子的錢！
Only way to make money dog!
有這種違約互換？
-I didn't know there were swaps on mortgages
現在就有了，陪他玩兒麼
There are now, we made it for him!
他腦袋估計塞屁股裡去了吧
His head must have caught up with his hole or do something... I don't know.
- 來一杯嗎 - 稍等
Want one? No?
傑瑞德
Jared
你聽說了蘭德和一個基金經理做的買賣嗎
Did you hear about the deal that Randall did with some fund-manager?
蘭德？扯蛋吧
Randall? Bullshit!
他沒腦子，肯定不是賺錢買賣
He's a foot-soldier, I'm sure it's a shit deal.
是真的！
No, It's for real!
* 傑瑞德·威內特
* Jared Vennett
跟你說過咱們會再見面的
I told you we'd meet later.
不巧是這種鬼地方，我平常不會來的
Unfortunately... It's in a place like this, which i would never be in.
我不和這些傻子下班後散心 我的朋友比他們有品味
I never hung out with these idiots after work, Ever! I had fashion friends.
看起來，確實有人要買2億的信用違約互換
Apparently this guy wanted two-hundred mill in credit default swaps.
蘭德也做成了買賣，你敢信？
Randall made the sale, can you believe it?
有人敢做空2億的房貸證券？
Somebody shorted two-hundred mill in mortgage bonds?
這還只是在德意志銀行…
That was just with Deutsche...
聽傳聞說，他掃遍了半個城市的銀行
Word is... he had half the town.
總共多少？
How much in total?
一共13億
1.3 billion
說什麼？
-What?
賽恩的流動資金也就這麼多啊！
That's... that's pretty much all of Scion's liquidity!
麥克，你這太過分了吧
Michael, that's highly distressing!
勞倫斯…我們流動資金沒用完！
Lawrence.... That is not all of our liquidity!
我覺得，你沒弄明白這買賣是怎麼回事
And I'm not certain that you really understand this trade.
這是必賺的錢
This is a certainty.
麥克，我和你平常是師生關係都好說
Mike, i consider myself a mentor to you.
但是這筆投資對公司絕對不合適
But our company is not comfortable with this investment.
- 我說話你聽明白了嗎？ - 勞倫斯
Am i being clear? - Lawrence
對於投資策略，我擁有完全自主權
I have full autonomy when it comes to investment strategy
你去看合同
You can read our agreement.
別給我扯官腔，麥克！
Do not throw our acception- agreement in my face Michael!
那是咱倆有內部共識的基礎上 現在你就像個瘋子一樣
We had an underlying understanding, you wouldn't act like a goddamn crazy man!
這不是瘋狂
This is not crazy....
這完全是邏輯推理
it's all very logical.
那現在我們就每月付費，坐等著房地產崩潰？
So now we pay up premiums on these swaps against housing-market until the mortgages fail?
也就是說…
In other words...
馬上就損失了幾百萬，除非天真塌下來？
we lose millions until something that has never happened before... Happens?
* “我是我命運的主宰，靈魂的統帥” * -英國詩人 威廉·亨利《永不屈服》
* I AM the MASTER of my FATE and the CAPTAIN of my SOUL
說的沒錯！
That's correct!
* 股市邏輯；房地產評估 全球市場上的知識產權
*STOCK MARKET LOGIC, The Appraisal of Real Estate Intellectual property in the global marketplace
* 亞當·斯密
*Adam Smith
* 我要賺錢，不是交錢，我要撤資了
* I want profits, not premium. withdrawal from fund
* 你瘋了嗎？信用違約互換？
*Have you lost your mind? Credit default swap?
* 信用違約互換？
* credit default swap?
* 房價大漲  *退錢
* Housing spike peak *withdrawing money
* 給信用違約互換交保費？？
*Premiums on credit default swaps??
* 有病吧 *為什麼我要交保費 *你得小心 *你想清楚了沒有？
* This is crazy *why am I paying premiums? * You should be careful * Have you thought this through?
- 你好 馬克 - 你好 凱茜
-Hello Mark Baum Oh hey Kathy!
- 別怪我，我下午有私事 - 我不是你的保姆
It wasn't me, I had a personal thing this afternoon. -I'm not your babysitter.
只要你給咱們摩根士丹利賺錢，我就開心！
If your appoint makes money for Morgan Stanley I'm happy!
好吧…聽說你要生了？
OK... Hey did I hear you're expecting?
那個…我們是打算要小孩…
Ehh, we're expecting to be expecting...
- 雖然我不好解釋得太清楚… - 那也是好事兒！
I'd be upset clearing this out, but we're .. - That's exciting!
蛋蛋那裡有個腫塊
Lump.. in my ball
我去檢查了一下
I'll go in for a scan -Hmm
結果是叫什麼“附睪”腫了
Turns out i have large thing, called an epididymis
這東西環繞著蛋蛋
Which is a thing that goes around the ball
好像下面兜著個口袋一樣
And is like a sack underneath.
我的附睪清晰可見 （附睪發炎）
* Inflamed epididymis I have an extremely pronounced epididymis
腫得和睪丸一樣大
Almost as large as another testicle on itself
夥計們聽我說，辛西婭…
So get this.... Cynthia.. Guys!
想讓我辭職不幹了！ 讓我在佛蒙特州開個過夜旅館
Cynthia wants me to quit! And open a B&B in Vermont.
挺好的主意！我挺想看你會怎麼開旅館
That's great! I'd love to see Mark Baum run a Bed and Breakfast!
估計是這樣：吃你的燕麥粥吧，傻逼！
Like: Here's your steel-cut oatmeal asshole!
馬克不願意討好那些能開出支票的顧客
Mark refused to kiss the ring of the people with the checkbooks,
所以才委屈自己在摩根士丹利旗下開設基金
so he had to set up his fund under Morgan Stanley's umbrella.
他的團隊也反映出他對金融系統的質疑態度
His small team his... distrust of the system.
你們一群變態！變態！
You guys are sick.. You're sick!
她說，這工作讓我不爽
She says, this job is making me unhappy.
可你不爽的時候反倒挺爽的
-But you're happy when you're unhappy!
我是在不爽的時候感覺挺爽的
I am happy when I'm unhappy!
文尼·丹尼爾 - 你知道怎麼做松餅嗎？
Vinny Daniel -You know how to make a muffin?
文尼是馬克手下懂數字的人
Mark's numbers guy.
你連怎麼洗衣服都不知道吧？鋪床呢？
Do you even know how to do laundry? Make a bed? -Okay!
文尼小的時候，爸爸就因為一場惡性犯罪去世了
Vinny lost his father to a violent crime when he was young
和馬克一樣，他也從來不說起這事
Just like Mark, he didn't talk about it.
我就是不說
-I don't talk about that!
辛西婭這麼認真，還真有可能趕他到佛蒙特州去
Cynthia's no joke, she could actually make him move to Vermont!
她都逼著我穿西服了
I mean, she made me start wearing a suit.
伯特·柯林斯，布朗大學的奧運會級別划船手
Porter Collins, former Olympic rower, went to Brown.
從上一個公司和馬克一起過來 搞不懂為什麼沒人聽馬克的
He worked with Baum at a previous firm, and couldn't figure out why no-one listened to Baum.
他覺得馬克提出的都是好點子
The guy with all the good ideas.
你是不是打錯電話了？ 這裡還有個叫頂尖基金的公司？
Sir, yeah, i know, do you have the wrong FrontPoint? Cause there is another front-point in this same building that is Baum's
丹尼·摩西，是這群人裡的樂天派
And Danny Moses, the optimist of the bunch.
他是交易鬼才 也這是大夥容忍他傻瓜式樂天派的唯一原因
And a hell of a trader, which is the only reason they put up with his bullshit optimism.
夥計，你對打錯電話的也太客氣了
You're a weird caller, you take longer with a wrong number than anybody else
這傢伙是德意志銀行的，說什麼做空房貸證券
I mean... it's this guy... from... Deutsche, who was talking about shorting housing bonds.
說到中間，我才聽出他找錯人了
And then, in the middle of the call where I had realized he had the wrong front-point.
然後他說想要找8層的那個公司
and then... and then... cause he wanted the one on the eighth floor.
- 他想要做空房貸證券？- 嗯
He wanted to short housing bonds? - Hmmm
每天至少5個撥錯的電話
-It happens like five times a day, that somebody uses the wrong front-point.
咱們得改個名了
We should change our name!
稍等，他想要做空房貸證券？
Wait, wait... He wanted to short housing bonds?
賭房價跌嗎？
Who bets against housing?
- 資產擔保證券指數到幾點了？- 這指數什麼意思？
- What's the ABX at? - What's ABX?
- 用來跟蹤次級房貸證券的價值 - 快睡你的覺！
-It tracks sub-prime mortgage bond value. -Go back to sleep!
指數在…
The ABX is at ... eh....
我的天！降下來了，去年到現在降了3點 這不對勁
Wow! it's down, It's down 3 points since last year, that's weird.
怎麼一點動靜都沒聽到過
I haven't heard a peep about that!
這人叫啥？傑瑞德…威內特
What was this guys name? Jared Vennett... Vennett
這是真的！這群中獎了的雜種因為我撥錯的電話
That's right! These lucky sons of bitches caught wind
抓住了華爾街歷史上最好的一樁交易
of one of the best trades in Wall-street history from a wrong number.
他們應該給我的錯誤電話線路抽成10%
They should've paid 10 percent to my fuck up state system
叫傑瑞德·威內特
He was Jared Vennett, Vennett
- 傑瑞德·威內特，德意志銀行，聽著就不靠譜 - 聽他說話就讓人不爽
Jared Vennett, from Deutsche, sounded very sketchy. -Sounds like a douche-bag.
- 你們好啊 - 請坐
OK.. Hi.... how are you?! -Have a seat!
來自德意志銀行的傑瑞德，我們洗耳恭聽了
Hey mister Vennett from Deutsche Bank, who do we have?
- 你和多少人聊過？ - 有幾個
So, how many people have you talked to about this trade? - A few.
有意向的還不少
There's definitely some interest.
噢
Ohh..
我老闆知道了非得弄死我不可
My boss would have my ass
你瘋了吧？傑瑞
are you crazy Jer?
別廢話！
Get lost!
滾蛋！
Fuck you!
所以你才打錯電話給我們
Which is why you're here talking to us on the wrong number?
- 聽著確實感興趣的人不少哇 - 好吧
Sounds like there's a lot of interest. -Alright.
有的人和我聊天就是看笑話尋開心 你們也不想談正事嗎？
A few people have us in, just to laugh at me on this deal, is that you?
你們也是這意思？
Is that what this is?
我們不是這類人，就馬克愛開這種玩笑
That's not what this is, that's just how Mark is.
和我們詳細說說
Let's see what you got.
- 你聞到什麼東西了嗎？- 什麼？
I'm sorry, do you smell that, what is that? - What?
- 這是什麼味道？ - 古龍水嗎？
What's that smell? -Cologne?
不…
No....
發財的機會！
Opportunity!
不…錢的味道
No... Money.
我聞到錢味兒了…
I smell money...
克里斯…
Chris....
- 手腳利索點 - 抱歉
goddammit! -I'm sorry.
這就是你們房貸證券的構成
This is your basic mortgage bond.
開始很簡單
Alright, the originals were simple.
就是幾千個3A級房貸組合起來
They were just thousands of AAA-mortgages bundled together,
政府擔保
guaranteed by the US-government.
而現代的房貸證券就不一樣了
The modern ones are different.
是私營的，而且由分層份額構成
They're private. And they're made up of layers of tranches.
* 份額一詞來源於法語，意為某物的一部分
*A tranche is a French word meaning "a portion of sth."
最高的3A級最先償還
Highest level AAA's getting paid first.
最差的B級最後還，會首先斷供
The lowest rated B's getting paid last, taking on defaults first.
顯然斷供的B級，能要回更多的錢來
No obviously if you're buying B's you could make more money.
但是有點風險，有時候也可能償還不了
But, they're a little risky, sometimes they fail.
克里斯…
Chris...
某處開始，有些B級或者2B級 從有點風險，變成狗屎貸
Somewhere along the line, these B's and BB's went from a little risky to dogshit.
垃圾桶在哪
Where's the trash?
我說的是最低的信用評分
I'm talking rock-bottom Fico-scores.
沒有收入核實
No Income-verification.
可調利率貸款…就是狗屎
adjustable rates... Dogshit!
違約率已經到了1至4個百分點
The default-rates are already up from one to four percent fellas.
等到了8%…也肯定會到的
And if they rise to eight percent... and they will!
那這些3B級的房貸也會一錢不值
A lot of these BBB's are going to zero too.
這…別離我這麼近
And that.... You're too close...
這就是發財機會
Is an opportunity.
你說8%的警戒線，現在已經到4%了？
OK, You're saying that at 8 percent the bonds fail and we're already at 4 percent?
- 沒錯 - 到了8就是世界末日了
That's right. -If they go to eight.... It's Armageddon.
- 是的 - 那怎麼沒人提到過這事兒
Yeah that's right. -How come nobody's talking about this?
你計算沒問題嗎？
And you're completely sure of the math?
好好看看他…
Look at him...
他是我的礦工！
That's my Quant!
你的啥？
-Your what?
我的量化研究員…我的數學專家！瞧瞧他！
My quantitative... My maths specialist! Look at him!
看到有什麼與眾不同的嗎？看看他的臉！
You notice anything different about him? Look at his face!
你這也太種族歧視了…
That's very racist
看看他的眼睛！我提示你們一下…
Look at his eyes! I'll give you a hint..
他的名字叫做“楊”！
His name is Yang!
他得了國家數學競賽的金牌…還是中國的競賽！
He won a national maths competition.. In China!
他連英語都不會說！
He doesn't even speak English!
所以沒錯！我對數字有信心
Yeah! I'm sure of the math.
其實我名字叫“江”
Actually, my name is JIANG
我也會說英語
and... I do speak English
傑瑞德喜歡這麼說，是想要讓我看起來更牛逼一些
Jared likes to say it though.. because he thinks it makes me seem more authentic
我…其實得了數學競賽第二名
And... i got second in that national math competition
所以你讓我們做空這堆積木嗎？
So.... You're offering us a chance to short this pile of blocks?
怎麼做空？
How?
用信用違約互換來做
With something called a credit default swap.
就像是證券的保險，不過如果證券完了 那你能拿到10倍的賠償
It's like insurance on the bond, and if it goes bust, you can make 10-to-1.
甚至有可能拿到20倍，崩潰趨勢已經開始了
Even 20-to-1 return, and it's already slowly going bust.
10倍，20倍，怎麼可能！
10-to-1, 20-to-1.... No way!
也沒人注意到
And no-one is paying attention.
沒人親自去了解
No-one is paying attention.
銀行忙著賣證券，暗地裡拿提成
Because the banks are too busy getting paid obscene fees to sell these bonds.
稍等…可你就是銀行的人
But wait.... You are the bank
你為銀行工作，那你的提成也富的流油吧
You work for the bank, i bet your margins are pretty nice and fat.
我的提成和這個沒關係
Let's not talk about my margins by the way.
這是我私事…好比我看你襯衫不錯 問你在哪買來的女裝，好玩嗎
Being nice and fat.... That's a nice shirt, do they make it for men?
你不替銀行說話？
Aren't you the bank?
我給銀行打工
I work for the bank!
我腦子沒賣給銀行
I don't think like a bank
大銀行小銀行，我賺的是錢
Big banks, small bank... I like to make money.
好吧…讓我直說
Alright...Let me put it this way....
這就像我來到失火大樓前面
I'm standing in front of a burning house,
現場讓你們買火災保險
And I'm offering you fire insurance on it
怎麼可能這些證券像你說得那麼差
-How can these underlying bonds be... as bad as you say?
沒人管嗎
It wouldn't be legal!
沒人知道裡面裝的什麼東西
Nobody knows what's in them!
沒人知道在證券裡有什麼鬼
Nobody knows, what's in the bonds,
我見到過65%達到3A評級的
I've seen some that are 65 percent AAA-rating.
其實95%都是次級狗屎
That i know, for a fact, are filled with 95 percent sub-prime shit.
信用評分都低於550 （FICO評分300-850，700以上認為是優）
With Fico's below 550
你就吹吧！
Get the fuck out of here!
真想被我吹暈了嗎？
Want me to really blow your mind?
要是市場覺得一個證券風險太高了怎麼辦？
When the market deems a bond too risky to buy, what do you think we do with it?
你們猜吧！
Take a guess!
我不知道，才讓你說
I don't know, you tell me!
好…
Alright...
你以為像書本上說的用倉單存貨抵押嗎？
You think we just warehouse it on the books?
假的，實際上我們重新打包 混上其他賣不出去的東西
No, we just repackage it, with a bunch of other shit that didn't sell
放到CDO裡面賣
and put it into a CDO.
- CDO？ - 對，這東西叫CDO
A CDO? -Yes... a CDO.
是什麼？
What is that?
把一些沒人買的B，2B，3B級爛貸
Where we take a bunch of B's, BB's and BBB's that haven't sold
打包成一堆…
and we put em in a pile...
數量差不多了，就忽然叫做“分散化投資”了
and when the pile gets large enough, the whole is suddenly considered 'Diversified'.
等著…評級機構的婊子們
and then... the whores of the rating agency,
評個百分之92到93的3A級別 其他屁都不放
Give it a 92 / 93 percent AAA-rating, no questions asked...
你再說一遍！
Holy... what! Say that again!
CDO，擔保債務憑證
(CDO)Collateralized Debt Obligations
理解CDO很重要，CDO才是讓房產危機…
It's important to understand, because it's what allowed the housing crisis
…禍害全國經濟的關鍵
become a nationwide economic disaster.
讓我們的世界頂級廚師安東尼·伯爾頓解釋一下
Here's world-famous chef Anthony Bourdain to explain.
假設我正給一個周日下午的大餐廳備菜
OK, I'm a chef on a Sunday-afternoon setting the menu of a big restaurant.
我周五定購的魚，就好比麥克做空的房貸證券
I ordered my fish on Friday, which is the mortgage bond that Michael Burry shorted.
有些魚…沒賣出去…
But... some of the fresh doesn't sell..
我也不知道原因，沒準這比目魚成精了…
I don't know why, maybe it just came halibut
有海豚一樣的智商
has the intelligence of a dolphin.
那我該怎麼辦呢？
So... what am i gonna do?
把這些3B評級的魚扔掉嗎？
throw all this unsold fish, which is the BBB-level of bond, in the garbage?
認虧了？
and take the loss?
沒必要！
No way!
我這麼心靈手巧…
Being a crafty and morally honorous chef that i am...
每種賣不掉的爛證券，我都扔到海鮮湯裡去
Every crappy levels of the bond i don't sell... i throw into a seafood stew.
這不再是爛魚！這是新東西！
It's not old fish! It's a whole new thing!
最妙的地方就在於…賣給顧客的名頭，是零售比目魚
The best part is.... They're eating retailed halibut!
這…就是CDO
That... is a CDO.
怎麼可能這些東西被攢到一起
I just need to know how these could possibly be correlated.
你好像《愛探險的朵拉》主人公 老是第一個發現大新聞
You're like D- D- Dora the Explorering, you're the first person who has found this...
稍等…你是說房貸證券是狗屎？
So.. hold on.. So mortgage bonds are dogshit?
CDO是貓屎包起來的狗屎
CDO's are dogshit wrapped in catshit.
對，就是這個理兒
Yeah... that's right!
機構們還把CDO當成國庫券一樣的寶貝
Institutions treat these CDO's like they're as solid as treasury bonds.
等著它們一錢不值吧
and they're going to zero..
不對啊，去年一年就賣了5千億的房貸證券
No, that can't be right, there, there, are 500 billion in housing bonds sold last year alone
信用評級機構，銀行 政府也摻和在裡面？
Ratings agencies, the banks.... the fucking government?
你這就像在說他們閉著眼開車
You're saying they're all asleep at the wheel?
沒錯！我整個部門都對這種狗屎流口水
Yeah! My whole department is long this stuff.
他們反倒叫我膽小雞仔
They call me chicken little.
他們叫我泡沫男孩
They call me Bubble-boy.
A級…廢了
A's ... Zero.
B級廢了，2B級廢了
B's.. Zero, BB's ..... Zero.
3B級…也是廢品
BBB's .... Zero.
接下來就是這個了！
And then that happens!
這…是啥？
What... is that?
這就是美國的房產市場
That's America's housing market.
- 謝謝 - 你說得好棒！
Thank you. - Fucking A Jared!
給我閉嘴！
Shut your fucking mouth!
再見 傑瑞德！
Bye Jared!
這不對勁
I don't like it!
他肯定有貓膩
He's playing us.
他在玩我們，他陷得太深了，拉人墊背來脫身
He's playing us, he's got too much skin in the game, and he's dumping his position.
要是他說的是真的呢
What if he's right?
- 你當然希望他說的是真的！ - 我是希望！
You want him to be right! -Yes, I do!
銀行給我們信用卡的利息是25%
The banks have given us twenty-five percent interest rates on credit cards.
助學貸款也坑了大家，普通人已經沒法脫身了
They have screwed us on student-loans, so we can never get out from under.
然後這傢伙，走到我辦公室裡說
Then this guy, walks into my office and says:
這些銀行太貪婪，已經忽視了市場真相了
"Those same banks got greedy, they lost track of the market"
然後我還能通過他們的愚蠢賺錢
And i can profit off of their stupidity
我靠！我當然希望他是對的！
Fuck! Yeah! I want him to be right!
你怎麼能不討厭他？ 你告誡我們注意的騙子特徵他身上全有
I mean, how come you don't hate this guy? He's everything you taught us not to trust!
我恨不起來！他這麼把自己的利益擺到檯面上 我倒挺尊敬他
You can't hate him! He is so transparent in his self-interest that i kinda respect him.
我會從這種人手裡買車嗎？肯定不會
Would i buy a car from him?... No!
但是他說的房貸市場情況是否屬實？ 咱們自己去調查看看，去調查
Is he right about the mortgage market? Let's find out. Let's find out!
我們只要回答兩個簡單問題
Look... It's two very simple questions:
房地產有沒有泡沫？如果有，銀行了解多少？
Is there a housing bubble? And if there is... how exposed are the banks?
咱們趕快行動，如果情況屬實
Let's get on this quickly too, because if he is right...
那有點錢的基金都會來找我們的麻煩
Every loser with a couple million bucks in a fund is gonna be jumping on us.
現在就出發！
Let's go!
摩根大通啊，這裡可是摩根大通啊
J.P. Morgan-Chase, J.P. Morgan-Chase.
*查理·蓋勒 別廢話了
* Charlie Geller OK.. Don't!...Stop Saying J.P. Morgan-Chase!
我覺得咱們能交好運
I got a good feeling about this
* 傑米·希普利 就一個會面，別抱太大期望
* Jamie Shipley Just a meeting though, you know...It's just a meeting!
會面天天都有…
People have meetings all the time... You know!
人們喝完咖啡，就去會面…
People drink their coffee, they have a meeting...
- 棕地基金？ - 我們在這兒！
Brownfield Funds? - Yes!  yes!
我叫克里斯，泰德交易團隊的前台
Hello, Hey! Chris... I 'm on Ted's Desk.
我叫查理，查理·蓋勒 我叫傑米，傑米·希普利
I'm Charlie, I'm Charlie Geller, I'm Jamie, Jamie Shipley.. Hi!
我們太想在你們的交易平台上接入了
We're so excited to get setup on your trading platform!
很好啊！先坐下聊一聊
Cool! Here, eh.. have a seat a second.
好的
Alright!
我…泰德讓我…先和你們見面聊聊
So I... Ted did ask ehm.. to do us some meeting in front.
可我一直找不到你們的宣傳資料
but I eh... I couldn't find any marketing material on you guys..
那個…我們是剛從科羅拉多州博爾德搬過來
Oh... we just moved here from Boulder.
我能看看你們的招募書嗎？
Oh, can we see some of your offering documents?
其實，棕地基金用的是…我們自己的錢
Well Brownfield has it own... money...
我倆的存款…嗯
It's our money... Yeah.
說說你們資金規模是多大？
Well can you tell us how much you manage?
好啊！我們現在做到3千萬了…
Of course! We're doing 30 million right now.... eh...
可是我們是4年前開始的 當時只有11萬的本錢
But we started four years ago, with a hundred-ten thousand.
- 厲害啊！- 所以你看
Wow! -So as you can see,
我們的投資回報率相當厲害
that's pretty phenomenal returns.
我們想和摩根簽署ISDA協議
We wanna get an ISDA-agreement with J.P. Morgan,
這樣我們就能交易長線期權了
So we can deal in long-term options.
- 想法很好嘛！- 是啊
-That's really cool! Yeah!
*ISDA協議（國際掉期及衍生產品協議）
*ISDA Agreement
*這個協議能夠讓投資者坐在“大亨”席位上
*An agreement that lets an investor sit at the "big boy table"
*阻止愚蠢的新手擾亂高水平的交易
*and make high level trades not available to stupid amateurs.
*押注很大的交易員，如果沒有ISDA
*Trying to be a high stakes trader without an ISDA
*就像騎著羊駝，想要贏得超級印地賽車比賽冠軍一樣
*is like trying to win the Indy 500 riding a llama.
你們的想法很好！
That is so cool!
謝謝！
Thank you!
不過呢…你們沒達到ISDA的資本準入門檻
But eh.. you guys are under the capital requirements for an ISDA.
差多少？
By how much?
嗯…差了…
Er.. How much eh...
十億四千七百萬
One billion four-hundred-seventy millions
所以…
So...
還差挺多
A lot!
這讓我們看起來挺不專業的，是嗎
This makes us look bad doesn't it?
我們連資金要求都不知道
That we didn't know what the capital requirements were.
怎麼說呢
I..... eh..
影響是不太積極
It's not great!
不過呢
But, eh.....
你們保持這樣的利潤率
Keep up those returns
以後發達了，記得再給我們打電話
And give us a call way down the line you know?
好嗎？
OK?
好的，謝謝你克里斯！
OK, of course! Thanks Chris!
- 祝你們好運！- 謝謝！
Have a good one guys! -Thank you Chris!
糟糕！
Shit!
誰會安排下午4點50談正事兒
Who the fuck schedules a meeting at 4:50 in the afternoon?
美國銀行和貝爾斯登沒回電話也就算了
Dude, B of A and Bear didn't even return our calls
- 連美聯銀行這種大眾貨也不屌我們！ - 是啊
and even fucking Wachovia blew us off! - I know man!
這是其他一樣在大廳裡就被拍死的傢伙的招股書
Here's the prospectuses of all the other losers who didn't make it past the lobby.
我真不想搞這個了…
I don't think i can do this anymore..
夥計，我還年輕，還能幹點正事兒！
Yo, I'm young yet, i can still do something with my life!
我想回科羅拉多老家 連大麻都比這邊的飄
I miss Colorado anyway. The weed's better!
先生們…請離開大廳
Gentleman... i need you to leave!
好，我們馬上走，咱們走
Yep, Yeah we're going, Let's go!
看這個！看看這個！
Look at this, Look at this!
這人說房地產市場就是一個大泡沫！
this guy says that the housing market is a giant bubble!
這部分情節和真實情況有些出入
OK, so this part isn't totally accurate.
我倆不是在大廳發現了傑瑞德的推銷資料
Now, we didn't find Jared Vennett's housing bubble pitch in a lobby of a bank that rejected us.
實際情況是，一個朋友告訴了查理這件事
Truth is... ehm.. A friend had told Charlie about it
我是從金融史學家Jim Grant的個人期刊上讀到的
And I read about it, in Grant?ˉs Interest Rate Observer
不敢相信！
This is crazy!
簡直像胡說的東西
This is..... crazy stuff!
這兒說房貸證券的信用違約互換
Here, they're saying that there's 10-to-1 returns,
是10倍的收益比
on Credit Default Swaps for mortgage backed securities
現在房地產市場馬上就要崩潰了
and the whole housing market is about to collapse.
對他倆來說，聽到這消息簡直像貓聞到了腥味一樣
For Jamie and Charlie, the housing market doomsday prediction was music to their ears!
bgm 《Lithium》by Polyphonic Spree
*bgm:  Lithium by Polyphonic Spree
他倆在傑米家的車庫創業起家
They had started working out of Jamie's garage,
資金是傑米在東海岸倒賣帆船攢下來的11萬
with a 110 thousand Jamie had saved taking sailboats up and down the east-coast.
我們的投資策略很簡單
Our investment-strategy was simple.
沒人願意聽到壞消息 所以人們往往低估壞事發生的概率
People hate to think about bad things happening so they always underestimate their likelihood.
簡單又高明的策略
Their strategy simple and brilliant.
他說的對！
What he said!
他倆發現，市場會低價販賣 認為不可能發生的事情的期權
Jamie and Charlie found: Markets will sell options very cheaply on things they think will never happen.
這樣損失會很小，而一旦得利…
So, when they were wrong, they were wrong small. But when they were right.......
- 就能賺很多！ -賺翻了！
They were right big! - Boooooom!
*期權交易的是“買賣權利”，不需要買賣實物
*options
*所以需要的資金量小，可以做空
（棕地基金） 幾年間他們就把11萬做到了3千萬
*BROWNFIELD FUND Within a few years they had turned a 110 grand into 30 million
是時候去紐約了…不過進展並不順利
Then it was time to go to New York City, And so far..... It wasn't going very well
要是這個買賣可以做呢？
So what if it does seem interesting?
不行，沒有銀行會和我們簽ISDA協議
Nope, no bank will give us our ISDA.
咱們沒風掀不起浪啊…
We're dead in the water...
這類交易完全搞不起
These kind of trades are totally out of the question!
咱們必須打電話給本
-We gotta call Ben!
打給他！
Call Ben!
本·瑞克是退下來的交易員 以前在摩根新加坡分行
Ben Ricker was a former trader in Singapore for Chase.
深深厭惡這一行就金盆洗手了
Quit the whole game in disgust!
當年在科羅拉多州，本正好是傑米的鄰居
He just happened to be Jamie's neighbor when they were in Colorado
因為本在遛狗，兩人才認識
They met, walking dogs....
不過本的世界觀更陰暗
But Ben was dark...
不只認為金融系統會崩潰
He didn't just think the whole system would fail
連全世界都會遲早毀滅
He thought the whole world was going down!
* 本·瑞克 沙拉…真好吃！
* Ben Ricket This salad's .... Oh.. hmmm good!
當然了，這些都是我花園裡新鮮采摘的
You know, every one of these vegetables is fresh from my garden
你們應該開一個自己的花園
You guys should start your own garden!
別用石油化工的東西污染土壤
What you gotta do is get your soil off petrol chemicals,
用木屑和尿來改良土壤，增加單硝酸酯
Use wood-ash and urine, help destroy the soil, creates mononitrate,
以後種子會成為硬通貨！
Seeds are gonna be the new currency!
不是孟山都公司的基因改造種子 我說的是原生態的健康種子
And not those Frankenseeds from Monsanto, I'm talking about good healthy organic seeds.
- 自己種菜，自給自足 - 這有點精神過敏了吧！
Make yourself a garden, learn to live off the land! - A fucking lunatic!
本有大銀行的實際經驗
Ben had real experience in a big bank,
傑米和查理連曼哈頓的銀行廁所都沒進過
Jamie and Charlie, never even been in a Manhattan bank bathroom!
但本明確說過金盆洗手，絕不再碰金融
But Ben was done with the banking world, he was very clear!
- 這點你想到了嗎？ - 咱們還是算清楚吧
Do you realize that? -Alright, let's crunch some numbers,
- 然後再打電話給本 - 我不想算來算去
Then maybe we'll talk about calling Ben - I don't wanna crunch the numbers,
- 每次咱們都是算了再決定的 - 你們兩個
When haven't we crunched the numbers? -Seriously guys!
- 趕快離開 - 好的，麻煩您了
-I need you out of here Of course, Yes Mam!
- 馬上就走 - 我們馬上走
One second! -We're going, we're going!
天哪，真是自找麻煩！這調研絕對是浪費時間
Oh god, i hate this! This is a total waste of time!
別擔心了，想開點
Come on! Would you relax!
城外45分鐘車程聽說有新房
there's a housing develpment about forty-five minutes outside of town.
我們要不就先去那裡看看
We may as well to check that out first.
希望一路上有古巴口味的餐館
I hope there's some Cuban restaurants on the way there,
聽說在邁阿密，古巴食品是一絕
because i heard the Cuban food is amazing in Miami.
你這麼開心簡直幸災樂禍
Please don't be Chipper in the face of me being miserable!
我恨你！
It really makes me hate you!
我想吃好的，還惹著你了
How is wanting to eat good food, being Chipper?
你好？
Hello?
有事嗎？你們想幹嘛
What's up man? What do you want?
我們正在調查已經90天斷供房貸的房主
Hello, I'm surveying mortgage owners who are over 90 days delinquent
我找哈維·漢姆西
I'm looking for a Harvey Humpsy
你找我房東的狗幹嘛
You want my landlord's dog?
你房東用狗的名字填了房貸申請表？
Your landlord filled out his mortgage application using his dogs name?
看來是咯！
I guess so!
等等，這混蛋沒有再交房貸嗎？
Wait, has that asshole not been paying his mortgage?
我可是一直在交房租啊！
Coz, I've been paying my rent!
他是有90天沒還房貸了
Well, yeah he is over 90 days delinquent
說真的
Seriously man!
我是不是要搬家了？
Am i gonna have to leave?
我小孩才剛安排好在這兒上學
My kids just got setup in this school man!
你好啊
Hey.... How are ya?
你得直接問問你的房東了
Ehm.. you should talk to your landlord about that
我這裡沒有什麼能幫到你的了
I'm sorry i don't have anymore information, but you ehm....
祝你們好運！
You have a great day!
真的…不會真的有事兒吧？
Seriously... Is everything gonna be ok?
你得問…你得問房東！
You should call... You should call him!
打電話給他！
You should give him a call!
錯不在我身上！我可是一直在交房租！
It's not my fault dude! I've been paying!
你好！
Hello!
好像有人走得很急
I think somebody just left
就搬走了電視
All they took was the TV.
這不對勁！
It's weird!
連廚房檯面都沒打掃
They didn't even clean up the counter
* 逾期通知
*PAST DUE NOTICE
* 總欠款5789 * 抱歉啦！
* Total Amount Due 5789. *Sorry!
老天爺
Oh, god!
簡直像核污染的切爾諾貝利
It's like Chernobyl!
這大概有100間房子，也就4個人在住
It's like a hundred houses, it can't be four people living here.
- 靠！
No, fuck that! -Shit!
*bgm: 《Barbarito Torres》by Lagrimas Negras
*bgm: Barbarito Torres by Lagrimas Negras
*bgm: 《Master of Puppets》by Metallica
*bgm: MASTER OF PUPPETS by METALLICA
* 奇幻小說《沙娜拉的後裔》 後裔Scion即為基金名字賽恩
* The Scions of Shannars
他在裡面呆了7個小時了
He's been there for seven hours
* 下跌9.3% 賽恩淨值
*-9.3% SCION VALUE
- 他在看什麼？ - 我聽說他崩潰了
What is he looking at? -I heard he had a breakdown!
已經破罐子破摔了
He?ˉs letting the fund tank
貝利博士辦公室
Dr. Burry's office
他還是希望你發郵件給他。稍等
No, he actually prefers that you e-mail him. Excuse me!
你好 勞倫斯！
Hey Lawrence!
我們對你預測宏觀經濟趨勢的能力沒有信心
We have no confidence in your ability to identify macro-economic trends.
你坐飛機來就為了說這個？
You flew here to tell me that? Why?
每個…個…人都能看出來房地產有泡沫
Every, E- E- Anyone can see there's a real-estate bubble
沒人能看出有泡沫，你的想法才是泡沫
Actually no-one can see a bubble, that's what makes it a bubble
這麼說太蠢了
That's dumb, Lawrence.
總有線索可以找啊！
There are always markers!
房貸欺詐
Mortgage fraud
2000年以後翻了5倍，平均收入卻沒漲
Quintupled since 2000 and the average take-home pay is flat, but ...
房價暴漲，意味著房子不再用來住 而是投資品
Home-prices are soaring, that means the homes are dead,not assets
那你這個硅谷來的麥克
So Mike Burry of San Jose, a guy who....
在連鎖理髮店理髮，不穿鞋
gets his haircut at Supercuts, and doesn't wear shoes,
你就比格林斯潘和財政部長懂得多？
knows more than Alan Greenspan and Hank Paulson....
我雖然沒和財政部長聊過，不過我確實更懂
I haven't talked to Hank, but yes he does.
你還挺萌啊！你這是在諷刺自己嗎
That's cute, that's cute! Are you being sarcastic with us Mike?
勞倫斯…我這人不懂什麼叫諷刺
Lawrence.... I don't know how to be sarcastic!
我也不會開玩笑
I don't know how to be funny
我不知道禮尚往來
I don't know how to ... work people..
可我對數據是真的懂！
I just know how to read numbers!
你現在做空多少了？
How big is your short position right now?
嗯…
Eh....
13億
1.3 billion
保費交多少？
And the premiums?
我們…大概…交…
eh, we pay ... eh... roughly...
8千萬到9千萬
80 to 90 million
每年交，有點多，畢竟咱們開了先例
Each year, which is surprising, because i was the first to do this trade
等著吧，肯定能賺錢！ 我最先趟的道，但方向是對的！
Watch, It will pay! I may have been early, but I'm not wrong!
你就會吹！你就會吹！
It's the same thing! It's the same thing Mike!
你管理的基金有多少？5億5千5百萬？
You're managing a fund of what? 555 million?
六年內，交保費就賠光了
In six years, it will all be gone!
單單這一項
On one bet
07年第二季度可調利率就發威了
The second quarter of '07 is when the adjustable rates kick in!
肯定會出現大批斷供
The defaults will skyrocket!
也就你這麼想！
Says you!
在合約到期前，基金裡有多少錢可以撤回？ 就算半年之內吧
How much is eligible for withdrawal before they're due? Say in the next two quarters.
如果你的投資人恐慌了的話
If your investors panic
3億零2百萬
不妙啊，麥克
My god Mike!
不會有人往外取錢的，那樣損人不利己
No-one will pull out, that would be suicide man
今年雖然下跌了17%，但相信我就行了 而且他們一直相信我
Down 17 percent for the year, but if they trust me, and they trust me!
沒人相信你！
No-one trusts you!
- 沒人！ - 我寫了幾封信給投資人了
No-one! -I've sent several e-mails to my investors
讓他們了解情況
Letting them know that the.. the....
07年的第二季度，我們房貸投資就能盈利
It's the second quarter of '07 is when our housing position shows returns
我說得很清楚了！
and ehm... I've been very clear!
你就等著大家撤資吧
People will withdraw their money!
為啥？誰會這麼傻？
Why? You'd have to be so stupid!
如果我們基金的資本減少過多
If, if  if the funds capital drops too much....
那麼互換合同就會自動失效
then the swaps contracts are voided
然後銀行…
and then the banks....
就會拿走所有錢，一個子兒都不剩
get to keep all of it, all of it!
合同會自動失效？
The contracts are voided?
The contracts are voided!?!
我去！
Holy shit!
你這臭不要臉的！
O, motherfucker!
麥克
Michael....
把我的錢還我
Give me my money back.
麥克，聽見了嗎？我要退回我的錢！
Michael, do you hear me? I want my money back!
你把我的錢給我！
Give me my fucking money back!
你這小兔崽子
You motherfucker!
房產市場正處在一個小不丁點的低谷裡
The market is in an itsy-bitsy little gully right now
好像大夥說“玩得太嗨了，咱們稍微緩緩神”
Like everybody said: "OK, that was crazy, let's just all calm down!"
那房子剛建成的時候，我35萬賣了出去
I sold that house for 350, the year it was built.
兩年以後，就值48萬，然後58萬5 這是一年半以前的價格
two years later... 480, then 585, maybe eighteen months ago.
這對夫妻在去年花65萬買了下來
This couple bought it for 650 last year!
倒霉碰上房價跌了，只能按原價賣唄
He'd let it go for that....high jump
他肯定覺得不值，不過會放手的
It will break his heart, but he'll let it go
那他為什麼要賣房？
Why is he selling?
夫妻倆現在都沒工作
Neither one is working right now
馬琳，你說他們急於出手是吧？
Marlene, you'd say they're motivated, right?
和這片的人積極性差不多吧
As motivated as one can be in this neighborhood.
左邊這房子，才是真正急於出手
This house on the left, I'd say they're properly motivated.
我說，急於出手的也太多了點
Wow! A lot of people seem very motivated.
房價小觸底嘛，大夥神經過敏
It's just a gully that's all. Just nerves
那…我們把車停到哪兒
So... where do we stand?
我得和我老婆商量一下
I need to talk to my wife
再等，過了這村就沒這店了！
ehm.. This market won't last!
其實，能給我介紹個房貸經紀人嗎？ 你推薦的，不錯的
Actually, can i talk to a mortgage broker? Anybody you recommend? Anybody you like?
有啊，是有個絕佳人選
Yes, yes, There's someone, absolutely!
這小妞肯定喜歡我啊 我幫她賺錢賺翻了
Yeah, bitch better like me, sent her ass to Cabo!
連摩根士丹利都等著要我們了？
So is Morgan Stanley recruiting us? Is that..
不是…銀行擁有我們的對沖基金
No, eh no. The bank owns our hedge-fund
但我們其實不歸銀行管 我們主要投資金融服務公司
We're not really a part of it, we invest in financial service companies.
我們過來是想了解這裡房貸行業的情況
We're trying to understand the residential mortgage business.
你每個月能辦多少筆貸款
How many loans do you write each month?
沒留意過，大概60筆吧
I don't know, about 60.
4年前呢？
What was it four years ago?
10筆…15筆的樣子
Ten.... but maybe fifteen.
以前我是酒吧招待，現在我連船都有了
I was a bartender, now i own a boat!
這裡面有多少是可調利率的房貸？ （*前幾年低利率，然後調高）
So, how many of these are eh.. adjustable rate mortgages?
嗯，絕大多數
Well, most.
是，我覺得有90%左右
Yeah, I'd say about ninety percent
近幾年這種房貸提成飆上天了
The bonuses on those skyrocketed a few years ago
我們全靠這個賺錢
Adjustables are bread and honey
那房貸申請有被拒的時候嗎
So, do applicants ever get rejected?
怎麼可能
Seriously?
要是他們被拒，我就不稱職了
Look if they get rejected I suck at my job!
他們沒錢也能貸到款？
Even if they have no money?
我們公司有一種“忍者貸款”
Well, my firm offers a NINJA loan.
不需要收入和職業證明，收入一欄空著都可以
No Income No Job Application, I just leave the income-section blank if i want.
公司不在乎
Corporate doesn't care.
- 大夥想要房，公司順應民意唄 - 你當然願意
- These people just want homes, and they go with the flow. - Good for you.
你們公司都不查驗的嗎
Your companies don't verify?
我星期五下午簽了房貸合同
If I write a loan on Friday afternoon,
大銀行周一中午就會買走
Big bank is gonna buy it by Monday lunch.
見怪不怪！我們也一樣
Deal! Same here!
- 你們能等會嗎？ - 行啊
Could you hold on a second? -Yeah
我搞不明白，為啥他們這麼坦白
I don't get it... Why are they confessing?
他們不是在坦白…他們這是在吹牛
They're not confessing.... They're bragging!
貸款的人真的知道這種貸款的風險嗎？
Do people have any idea what they are buying?
我一般找移民
I focus on immigrants!
等他們還不起房貸睡大街了… 你讓他們簽什麼都願意
Once they find out they're getting homeless.. They'll sign where you tell em to sign.
不會問問題，不理解利率是什麼東西
They don't ask questions, don't understand the rates.
你也找移民下手嗎？
And you targeting on immigrants too?
移民的信用分對他來說還太好
Their credit isn't actually bad enough for him.
我不跟錢過不去
Look I'm a yield guy
一筆固定利率的良性房貸，我只賺兩千
I make two thousand on a fixed rate prime
可做一筆可調利率的次級貸，我能賺一萬
But i CAN make ten thousand on a sub-prime adjustable
說真的，沒有脫衣舞女郎的幫忙 我也開不上寶馬7系
Trust me, I'm not driving that 7-series without strippers
她們信用評分都不行，可是都超級有錢
No-one on the pole has good credit, and they're all cash-rich.
我好像聽沃倫·巴菲特說過類似的話
I think I read Warren Buffett said something like that.
啥？巴菲特是誰？
What? Who's Warren Buffett?
你說的脫衣舞女郎…就是露肉的那種？
OK, So, strippers.... like exotic dancers...
光屁股的
Nude, you know
露著胸的
Topless..
- 脫衣舞女郎 - 對
Strippers? -Yeah, Hmmmm.
- 能幫我們介紹個嗎？ - 當然行
Can you introduce us? Yes!
沒問題！
Yes!
我一直選還貸方式多的可調房貸 我畢竟是自由職業者
I always get option-pay adjustable. I'm a private contractor.
聽不清，抱歉！
Can't hear you, I'm sorry!
我一直選還貸方式多的那種可調房貸 我自己乾，需要點靈活性
I always get option to pay adjustable, I'm a private contractor, i need the flexibility.
你怎麼跟房貸公司說你的職業
And you tell the mortgage company what you do?
我寫的是：治療師
I write: Therapist
- 你可以摸我！ - 一直？
You can touch me! -Always?
那隻能在VIP房間
Only in V.I.P.
不不不，誤會了 你說你一直選可調利息房貸
No, no, no you say you always do adjustables
你一套房子不止一筆貸款嗎？
And you have more than one loan on a property?
大夥都這樣
Everybody does!
- 至少我們這兒這樣 - 我沒聽明白
At least down here -I'm sorry what?
每個人都這樣！至少我們這兒是！
Everybody does! At least down here
這樣首付只要5%
That way you'll only put down like five percent
可房價現在不漲了，對吧？
Well prices have leveled off though, right?
是啊，暫時不漲
Yeah, it's a gully
你能不能別晃來晃去的？我照樣付你錢
Would you mind not moving anymore? I'll still pay you!
抱歉…有人盯著
Sorry... We're not alone.
你聽我說…如果房價不漲
OK, look.. If home-prices don't go up,
你就不能重新貸款了
You are not going to be able to refinance
你就陷到房貸裡脫不開身
And you're going to be stuck paying
等利率優惠期過了，月供漲到多少是多少
whatever your monthly payment is once it jumps up, whenever your teaser rate expires
加上逾期的利滾利，可能漲到200%到300%
Your monthly's could go up two- to three hundred percent!
詹姆斯說我總可以重新貸款的！
James says i can always refinance!
那…他…就是個騙子
Well... He's ... A liar.
至少對這種情況，他很可能是錯的
Actually in this particular case, James probably is wrong.
200%？
Two-hundred percent?
我所有房貸的？
On all my loans?
你什麼意思？不就是一套房兩筆貸款嗎
What do you mean? We're talking about two loans on one house right?
我有5套房
I have five houses
外加一套公寓房
And a condo..
有泡沫！
Hey, there's a bubble!
你怎麼知道的？
How do you know?
相信我，打電話給傑瑞德
Trust me. Call Vennett,
買上5千萬房貸證券的信用違約互換
Buy 50 million in swaps on the MBS
買哪個？Garabaldi 4，3B評級！
What do we got? Garabaldi IV, Triple B!
馬克，你確定嗎？
Mark, are you sure?
確定！這泡沫太扯淡了！
Yeah, yeah! It's time to call bullshit!
哪些有泡沫？
Bullshit on what?
這兒全都是泡沫！
Every fucking thing!
*重新貸款:房價上漲,借房貸的人通過重新貸款 可獲得最新的更低利息房貸，代價是延遲還清
* explain refinance
*銀行可以把房貸當作"未來收款權"賣給投資人 所以銀行有動力重新貸款，這樣可以當新的再賣一次
*銀行的分期還貸計劃，一般前期是優先還利息 所以重新貸款後，原放貸銀行並不吃虧
* explain refinance
*而房價下跌時,銀行無法賣出房貸給投資人 自己承擔風險,就不再願重新貸款了
是美國最暴走的對沖基金嗎？
Is this America's angriest hedge-fund?
聽好了，我還有最後一個問題問你
Hi listen, I got one last question for you
你想怎麼蹂躪我們？
How are you fucking us?
何必說的這麼露骨呢…文尼
There's a nice way to say that Vinnie...
我沒開玩笑
I'm serious
我們會買你的互換 但前提是你說清楚打算怎麼蹂躪我們
We'll buy your swaps, but only if you say how you're fucking us.
我不想蹂躪你，文尼，我想要親吻你
I'm not fucking you Vinnie, I'm kissing you
看著你的雙眼，讓你爽
I'm looking deep into your eyes as i make love to you Vinnie.
我正和盤托出本世紀最好的買賣給你
I'm handing you the deal of the century on a fucking platter!
我能得到什麼好處？
What do I get out of it?
這還不簡單…我之前做的證券每月賠進去2千萬
Easy..I got a 20 million a month negative carry
老闆早就想要了我的命，認為我神經不正常了
I got bosses trying to pull the plug, because they're thinking I'm out of my fucking mind
明白嗎？
Alright?
我們做成了這筆買賣，我之前的問題都不是事兒
We make this trade, those problems aren't so big anymore
當然了…互換是黑市
And sure... Swaps are a dark market so...
怎麼定價我說了算
I set the price, whatever price i want.
等你收回投資的時候，我肯定會讓你大出血
And when you come for the payday, I'm gonna rip your eyes out
從你那裡大賺一筆
I'm gonna make a fortune
但好消息是，你也不會在乎的
But the good news is Vinnie, you're not gonna care
因為你賺的錢太多，你都沒空管我
Cause you're going to make so much fucking money!
這就是我能得的好處
That's what I get out of it
想知道你能得到什麼嗎
Wanna know what you get out of it?
你現在先拿到冰淇淋，熱巧克力 香蕉和堅果配料
You get the ice-cream, the hot-fudge, the banana and the nuts!
我現在能拿到裝飾糖粒
Right now I get the sprinkles
如果這事兒最終能成
And yeah.... if this goes through...
我能吃到頂上的櫻桃
I get the cherry.
但你能吃到聖代冰激凌
But you get the sundae Vinnie
除了櫻桃，剩下的全是你的！
You get the sundae!
行，我信你
Alright, I'll buy that.
謝謝你解釋
Thank you!
那你拿個主意
So what do you say?
想讓我幫你坐莊嗎？
Want me to make you a market?
我們買5千萬
We'll take 50 million
Garabaldi 4，3B評級
Garabaldi-4 Triple-B
準備好籤字筆吧，我來準備好文書
Sharpen your pencils, I'll get the paperwork ready
我就那個了
Aahhh... Fuck you too!
好！
YES!
這就對了！
that's right!
* 2006年5月
* 2006 May
他電話號碼太多，我老忘了
He has so many numbers, and i always forget,
- 應該打哪個電話，他明確和我說過 - 就先選第一個吧
Which one he prefers, cause he's very specific! -Just pick the first one
- 不知道對不對 - 試試吧
I don't know if it's the first one -Just try it!
好吧
OK
*2002美國司法部長自己創作 並當眾演唱的愛國歌曲《讓雄鷹高飛》
*bgm Let the Eagle Soar by John Ashcroft
*他因推行愛國法案侵犯隱私等行為 廣受爭議，媒體常用此歌來惡搞諷刺
* explain about John Ashcroft
*（成年人每月用水量）
*Adult One Month Stacked Water Usage Chart
*（彭博金融資訊）
* Bloomberg
我是本·瑞克
Ben Ricker
本你好，我是傑米
Hey Ben it's Jamie!
傑米，我告訴過你不要打這個電話
Jamie, you know you're not supposed to use this line.
我就知道…
Told ya...
試試這14個號碼的第2個
OK, let's try number two out of fourteen.
本·瑞克
Ben Ricker
本，你這不是自找麻煩嗎？ 你都退休了好吧
Ben, why do you do that man? You're a retired trader, ok..
- 沒人監聽你電話 - 國安局有520億的預算
No-one is listening to your calls! -The NSA has a 52 billion dollar budget
每秒能監聽上千萬個電話 你以為他們吃閑飯的？
and the ability to monitor tens of millions calls a second, you think they're not using it?
那我保證不會在一句話裡同時說
OK, I promise i will refrain from saying,
你的名字和放射髒彈這詞
Ben Ricker and dirty bomb in the same sentence
- 我的天 - 真受不了
Jesus! -I'm sorry dude!
本·瑞克
Ben Ricker
你看到我們發給你的東西了嗎
Did you get a chance to look at what we sent you Ben?
我是查理，我也在旁邊
It's Charlie.... I'm here too!
查理，你好，我看了，稍等！
Hi Charlie, Yeah I did, Hold on!
本，你還聽著嗎
Ben, you still there?
嗯
Yeah
我就直說吧
I'll be honest gentlemen
你倆把我嚇壞了
you scared the shit out of me!
那說明這是真東西對吧？這叫傑瑞德的傢伙沒胡說
That's a good thing right? That means that this Vennett guy is not wrong!
是沒有
No, he's not!
太好了
Cool
你們對CDO還了解什麼
Tell me more about these CDO's
好的，傑瑞德只是提到了CDO (*擔保債務憑證，再打包的房貸證券)
Yeah yeah, ehm, OK Vennett mentioned the CDO's, but actually,
- 我倆實際看了，情況比他想的還糟 - 數據離譜的像假的一樣
We took a look and they're way worse then even he realizes -These things don't even make sense Ben.
- 連預測模型都用不了 - 打包的CDO比房貸證券規模還要大100倍
We can't even model them -It's a hundred times bigger than the MBS
然後有90%還是3A評級？
and ninety percent AAA-rating?
- 是啊，超過90% - 乾的漂亮
Yes, over ninety percent - Incredible!
我仔細看了你打算做空的CDO
Yeah, I took a good hard look at the CDO's you want to short.
天才的想法！CDO就是包裝精美的屎
They're brilliant! Worthless, total crap!
傑米，厲害厲害！
Jamie, very good!
怎麼說呢…我找屎還挺擅長的！
What can i say.. I, I'm, I'm, good at finding shit!
本，我們打算做空2B和3B級別的 風險也相對小一些
So Ben, we shorted the BB's and the BBB's, and the risk is relatively low,
回報率差不多是25倍
Pay-up is like 25-to-1
那你們找我幹啥？我洗手不幹了
OK, so why are you calling me? I don't do this anymore!
本，我們…
Look, Ben...
我們需要你幫忙搞定ISDA協議
We need you to help us get the ISDA.
有了持槍證，我們就能開乾了
If we get a hunting license, we can short this crap
我們知道你恨華爾街 所以不會讓你去做交易
We know you hate Wall-street, we're not asking you to do the trading
只是，請求你…
We're simply asking you to...
幫助我們
To help us.
能坐到“大亨”席位就行
To get a seat at the fucking table
那種地方可是烏煙瘴氣的很
It's a pretty ugly table guys
本，整個系統已經出大亂子了
Look Ben, the system fucked up in a big, big way here, OK?
我們比所有人都先得到了消息
And somehow... we , eh.. know before anyone else.
這是絕對是千載難逢的機會！
You know, this is a once in a lifetime deal!
我在考慮
I'm thinking
好，我打電話給德意志銀行
OK, I'll call Deutsche Bank
太感謝你了，本！
Thank you Ben!
還有貝爾斯登公司，那裡也有些把柄可以抓
Oh and Bear, what about Bear? They have some apprehensible product!
好，貝爾肯定來者不拒
-OK, Bear will trade with anybody!
* 歡迎來到紐約    市長麥克·彭博
*WELCOME TO NEW YORK CITY Mayor Michael Bloomberg
bgm: 《Feel Good Inc》by Gorillaz
* bgm: Feel Good Inc by Gorillaz
（駱駝上的鐵屋子正越來越熱）
*(song) City's breakin' down on a camel's back
（逆來順受的他們還裝睡不醒）
*(song) They just have to go 'cos they don't know whack
（娛樂至死的東西更吸引眼球）
*(song) So all you fill the streets it's appealing to see
（有被洗腦的自由又何必逃脫）
*(song) You won't get out the county, 'cos you're bad and free
（你們追求名利去醉生夢死）
*(song) You've got a new horizon it's ephemeral style
（陰沉的地方人人抑鬱寡歡）
*(song) A melancholy town where we never smile
（我只想聽到外面希望之聲）
*(song) And all I wanna hear is the message beep
我看看能不能把材料遞上去
I'll see if i can push it through
幫我們謝謝傑瑞德
And oh, thank Jared for us.
（僅存的夢想讓我不敢入睡）
*(song) My dreams, they gotta catch me, 'cos I don't get sleep, no
*2007年6月29日，iPhone第一代發售
*June 29, 2007, iPhone first release
*2007年伊拉克戰爭，美國開始撤軍
*2007, Iraq War, began withdrawing
*Trinette拍攝的在加長轎車裡享受的夫婦
*couple on Trinette Reed,photo by Trinette Reed, before Great Recession.
*真相就像詩詞
*Truth is like poetry.
*可絕大多數人都討厭詩詞
*And most people fucking hate poetry.
*在華盛頓一個酒吧偶然聽到
*-Overheard at a Washington, DC. bar
*斷供的房貸達到新的1百萬高點
*Mortgage delinquencies hit new high nearly 1 million...
*2007年1月11日
*2007. Jan. 11
是我，馬克，現在就把電話轉給文尼
Hi, it's Mark, I need to talk to Vinnie right now!
稍等
Wait a second
我們就是想讓你們解釋清楚…為什麼
we just asking you to explain to us.. we need to know why
我們看到的和你說的完全不同
just how it is that you are fucking us, because what we are seeing here is..
快去摩根士丹利大廈！
Morgan Stanley building fast!
我們屏幕上顯示的東西難道不一樣嗎？ 能不能讓同一個人和我們說話
Are we hooked up at the same computer-screens? -Can we talk to one person please?
你說你在哪兒？
OK, yeah. -What do you mean, you're in the tower?
文尼，能聽見吧？
Vinnie, are you there?
- 馬克，我能聽見 - 你聽說了嗎？
Mark, are you there? Hello? -Yeah, Yeah, Did you hear?
房貸斷供已經破記錄了
Mortgages defaults have gone through the roof!
你那裡房頂有人跳樓嗎？
Anybody jumping off the building yet?
為什麼要跳？次級貸證券可是在上漲
Why would they? Sub-Prime mortgages are up
- 怎麼可能？ - 傑瑞德讓我們今天再投入190萬的抵押
What? -Vennett wants 1.9 million more in collateral by-close
傑瑞德讓我們追加抵押
Vennett's asking us to post collateral
怎麼會這樣？
What the hell is going on?
不知道，但德意志銀行電話一直在催
We don't know, but Deutsche is on the phone demanding payment
- 把傑瑞德給我叫過來，這小畜生！ - 給傑瑞德打電話
Call Vennett, call that little shit! -Call Vennett!
讓他快點滾過來
Tell him to get his ass down here
次級房貸斷供越來越多
So, sub-prime loans go bad,
但是它們組成的房貸證券卻更值錢了？
but sub-rime bonds, which are made up of sub-prime loans, are more valuable?
我也奇怪，他們要今天必須交齊1千9百萬
I know. They want another 1.9 million by market close
信用評級機構呢？穆迪公司？標準普爾？ 他們調低了CDO或房貸證券的評級嗎
What about the ratings-agencies? Moody's, S&P? Are they downgrading the CDO's or mortgage bonds
- 現在評級什麼樣？ - 還是原封不動
Where are the ratings of this? -They're the fucking same!
沒變，還都是3A評級
Nope, They're all still AAA!
見鬼了！
What the hell!
在逗我？這幫混蛋，不要臉的！
Are you fucking kidding me? Those fuckers, those motherfuckers!
他們對外評級以後就鑽到錢眼裡去了
They go public and all the care about is their bottom-line and their shit!
馬克，還有事…
Mark, that's not all...
摩根士丹利風險部的過來了 他們找了你老闆
The Morgan Stanley risk-guys are here -They called in Kathy Tao
想說服她賣掉我們的互換
I'm trying to convince her to make her sell us swaps
他們覺得這些保費肯定是被套牢的買賣
Apparently eh, tying up securing some insurance payments
等著房地產崩潰是不明智的投資
So, a housing Armageddon is not prudent investing.
老闆怎麼說？
What did Kathy say?
沒表態，她一直問這是不是你的核心投資
Nothing yet, she keeps asking if this is one of your crusades
明白了，你走過去，語氣平靜，非常禮貌的
OK, I want you to walk back in there and very calmly, very politely
讓這些風險評估師都滾蛋
Tell the risk-assessors to fuck off!
然後過來和我在標準普爾碰頭 我們要找喬治亞聊聊
And then meet me over at Standard & Poors, we're gonna talk to Georgia
把傑瑞德那混蛋叫過來 看我不把他腦漿打出來
Get that fuck Jared Vennett I want to bash his fucking head in
嗯…各位
Uh, gentlemen...
我剛和馬克·鮑姆談過了
I spoke with Mark Baum
他的原話：都滾蛋
He says: to fuck off!
*紐約百老匯大道，銅牛
*New York, Broadway, Charging Bull
*百老匯大道25號，標準普爾評級機構
*Standard & Poor's Ratings Agency, 25 Broadway
我眼睛不好使啊
I don't see a damn thing.
我選的眼科醫生總是特別忙
Aaah, my eye-doctor is always busy
只要能預約上我就得去 今天上午就這麼廢了
I end up taking any appointment they'll give me and then the whole morning gets shot to hell!
那麼…
So...
好咧
Alrighty
頂尖基金的朋友們
FrontPoint Partners
標準普爾有什麼能幫到你們的嗎
How can Standard & Poors help you?
我們想弄明白，為什麼評級機構 不下調次級貸證券的評級
Well, we don't understand why the ratings-agencies haven't downgraded sub-prime bonds
證券包含的房貸，很明顯情況在惡化
since the underlying loans are clearly deteriorating
斷供率是讓人們擔心了 不過數字波動還在我們的合理模型之內
Well, the delinquency-rates do have people worried, but they're actually within our models
那…
So
你說沒事就沒事？
Says you?
你確信這些證券裡的房貸是可靠的？
You're convinced the underlying mortgages in these bonds are solid loans?
- 這是我們的觀點 - 打開天窗說亮話
That is our opinion yeah. -Oh crack the tape!
你看過底層房貸的數據嗎？
Have you looked at the loan-level data?
- 你以為我們整天在幹啥 - 現在只要有信用分，就肯定能拿到房貸
What you think we do here all day? They're giving these loans to anyone with a credit-score and a pulse
打斷一下，你認為我們工作是什麼？
Excuse me sir, what do you think we do here all day?
我不明白，要不我們也不會過來
Not sure, I guess that's why we're here.
我不明白
What I don't understand
我們再三反覆核對過了！
We can't re-recheck  and then check again!
如果這些房貸證券這麼穩定可靠
If these mortgage-bonds are so stable, so solid
你先檢查一下你同事吧
you should check your friend
你有沒有…
Have you ever refused to rate?
- 做你的夢吧 - 我們有理由這麼評級
that's delusional! -We stand behind it
你有沒有給過這裡任何一個證券 評級低於3A級別？
Have you ever refused to rate any of these bonds upper-tranches AAA?
我們能看看對應的材料嗎？
Can we see the paperwork on those?
我沒有義務給你們看內部信息 不管你是誰
Oooh, I'm under no obligation to share that information with you, whoever you might be.
你就回答我的簡單問題 給我們個去年低於3A評級的名字
Just answer the question Georgia, can you name one time in the past year?
你去看了實際數據 最後也沒有給銀行想要的3A評級
Where you checked the tape and you didn't give the banks the AAA-percentage they wanted?
如果我們不這麼評，人家就去隔壁的穆迪評級了
If we don't give them the ratings, they'll go to Moody's right down the block.
我們不配合，那我們的對頭就會搶走客戶的錢
If we don't work with them they will go to our competitors
這地方就這麼運轉，我們有什麼辦法
Not our fault, simply the way the world works.
- 我靠！- 明白了吧
Holy shit! -Ah yes, now you see it!
我什麼都沒說過！
And I never said that!
你們就是賣信用評級的賺錢機構
You're selling ratings for fee's
信用商店
A ratings shop
你們不賺這麼多錢也能維持運行啊
You could afford to make less, make less.
沒人這麼要求我
Nobody said that!
這不是我能做主的，我有老闆管著
And it is not my decision, I have a boss.
- 你在逗我？ - 我沒空跟你開玩笑
Are you kidding me? -No I am not kidding you!
這就是你的立場？
Is that the angle you're taking?
這意思是只要有老闆的人…
So now anybody who has a boss,
都不用為任何圖財害命的勾當負責了！ 你當自己四歲小孩嗎
Can't be held responsible for doing shitty and illegal things! -What are you? Four?
我不是四歲孩子
No, eh, eh, I am not four!
不是不負責！
Mister Baum, I am not, no!
我倒奇怪，你們來找我的動機是什麼
And I wonder, I wonder, what your incentives might be.
是不是評級變了，對你們有好處啊？
Is it maybe in your best interest to have the ratings changed? Is it, perhaps?
信用違約互換你們買了多少？
How many credit default swaps do you own?
立場和對錯是兩回事
Doesn't make me wrong
你倆還裝什麼好人！
just makes you a hypocrite!
bgm: 《District Divided》by Darkest Hour
* bgm: District Divided by Darkest Hour
*下跌11.3% 賽恩淨值
*-11.3% SCION VALUE
房貸斷供，房貸證券卻更值錢了，真見鬼了
Mortgage-delinquencies went up and the CDO's got more valuable, unbelievable!
是啊，走勢太反常了！
We know, it's completely backwards!
我給貝爾斯登公司的朋友打電話 他連CDO是啥都不知道
I just called an old friend at Bear he didn't even know what a CDO is.
是啊，我剛給貝爾和德意志匯過去7萬塊錢
Yeah, I just had to wire Bear and Deutsche seventy thousand dollars
這感覺，就好像現在二加二等於…
It's like two plus two equals...
屎！
Fish!
好啊
Great!
這裡面顯然有黑幕
You bought into a rigged game
要是錢賠光了，我就得回去家裡蹲
We lose everything.. -I'm gonna have to move back in with my mom!
我可不想我媽管我
can't do that
我等會還有事兒忙
Well, alright i got a colon in a couple of mins
等一下，別掛電話
Wait a minute, hold on! Ben!
本，聽我說
Ben, look!
有可能銀行完全不懂CDO是什麼東西，或者
Either the banks are clueless and they don't know how to value these CDO's or...
或者他們想用沙子把屎蓋起來，藏著掖著
they're suck crooks that... the CDO's are worth shit, and they're hiding it!
我覺得我們應該再買更多！
I think we should buy more swaps!
- 你說啥？ - 別廢話，合同上白紙黑字寫得清楚
- What? -Suck it up and pay up fellas we made a deal
不行！不行！
No way, No!
你小子玩我們嗎，還有臉過來
Are you fucking kidding me? you come in here you fuck up -Are you fucking seriously?
- 不不不！ - 行！
No, no, no! -Yeah!
你腦子燒了嗎
You're unbelievable!
不行不行不行！
No, no, no!
建議你每年灌一次腸來排排毒
Seriously, colonic once a year!
你就是個跑腿的，裝逼不成等著被揍吧！
Ass! -You got a matching little butler-boy you butt-fuck!
都發泄完了？
Are you done?
- 完了… - 剛才大聲罵，我都閃腰了
Think so yeah -God i pulled a muscle in my back from yelling
房貸斷供率一直在漲
Mortgage defaults have done nothing but go up!
你給我們房貸證券的報價還更高了
Yet you quote us a higher price on the bonds
你給我解釋清楚！這顯然不合道理
Please explain that to me! There's no way that makes sense!
你的量化方法絕對有問題
There's no way you're marketing these swaps appropriately!
有什麼理由讓我們繼續乾？
I mean, why shouldn't we back out of this trade right now?
我說沒說過，咱們談成買賣的時候 評級機構，美國證券交易委員會
Didn't I say, that when we made this deal, that the rating-agencies, the SEC
大銀行們全都不懂？說沒說過？
and the big banks were clueless! Didn't I say that?
- 說過沒有？ - 有說過的，有說過的
Didn't I say it? -Yes you did, you did!
閉嘴！
shut up!
他們腳都開始著火了，心裡卻想著牛排應該烤熟了 你還覺得奇怪？
now their foot's on fire and they think their steak is done, and you're surprised?
這不是愚蠢，這是詐騙
That's not stupidity... that's fraud!
你跟我說清楚愚蠢和違法的區別 我就去把我小舅子抓起來
Tell me the difference between stupid and illegal and I'll have my wife's brother arrested.
- 挺好笑的！ - 你們還是沒弄明白整個系統有多蠢
That was funny! -I guess you just don't realize how clueless the system really is!
我承認，是有一些見不得人的勾當
Yes, there's some shady shit going down!
但相信我，這是愚蠢驅使的
but trust me, it's fueled by stupidity!
看看你們這些人
Look at yourselves!
都覺得自己是敢於懷疑的人
You know you passed yourselves off as cynical people but....
可你們還對這幫青天大老爺抱有希望？
You still have some faith in the system don't you?
我是不抱
I don't
文尼是明白人！
Well, except for Vinnie!
誰在乎？
Who gives a shit?
- 不行！- 聽我說
No way! -Look!
要麼我們對，要麼我們錯得離譜
Either we're right, or we're wrong in a giant, giant way!
如果真錯了，得找高人給我們點醒才行
And if we're wrong then we gotta find someone to help us get out of this trade
我現在是一點都不覺得我們占理
I'm not feeling remotely confident that we're right
萬一咱們錯了
And, and... If we're wrong
誰來告訴我們？有誰懂？沒人懂！
Who's gonna tell us? Who understands this stuff? It makes no sense!
我們應該去拉斯維加斯！
I think we need to go to Vegas!
- 那兒有什麼？ - 去哪兒幹啥
What's in Vegas? -Vegas!
拉斯維加斯又能有什麼東西？
What the hell is in Las Vegas?
下周那裡召開美國證券化論壇年會
The American Securitization Forum is there next week
每個證券、CDO、次級貸、倒賣交換的交易員都會去
Every bond and CDO-salesman, sub-prime lender and swap-trader is gonna be there
我這麼說
I'm telling you
你掙的是他們手裡的錢
Your bet is against their money,
是時候去看看人傻錢多是怎麼回事了
it's about time you find out just how dumb that money really is
我真不喜歡拉斯維加斯
God no, I hate Vegas!
聽說吃的東西特別好，那裡也有松久壽司店了
I hear the food has gotten really good in Vegas, they have a Nobu now
你能不惦記著吃嗎
could you fucking stop!
*美國證券化論壇，拉斯維加斯
*American Securitization Forum, Las Vegas
bgm:《The Phantom of the Opera》by Andrew Webber
*bgm: THE Phantom of the Opera, by Andrew Lloyd Webber
*汽車抵押貸款 工資日貸款
*Auto Title Loans & Payday Loans
*凱撒宮酒店
* Caesars Palace
*擇一抵押公司CEO保羅·丹頓
* Option One CEO Paul Dantone
*房貸市場仍然穩健，後勁十足
* The Mortgage Market is Strong & Getting Stronger
證券“貴”的意思是？
... in a sense? -If the bond is "rich", it is...?
只說明證券定價過高
that just means it's overpriced
- 飛機上睡不著我就自己準備了一下 - 咱們集中精神！
I can't sleep on a plane so I did my homework -OK, let's focus!
我們是為了什麼來的？
What's our goal?
搞清楚這買賣是千載難逢的機會
Figure out if this is a deal of a lifetime or...
還是別人比我們懂得都多 咱們回頭會虧大發了
everyone knows here something we don't and we're gonna get royally screwed
和貝爾公司的人接觸的時候 注意你們的目的
Right, remember that when you meet with guys from Bear!
我給你們安排見面機會
I'll set you up with a face-to-face
好的，地方在哪？
Awesome, where is that?
我的天！5年前這年會還是窮鬼聚會
Holy shit! Five years ago Securitization was a loser-convention
也就有100到200人出席
a hundred, maybe two-hundred people would show
產業每年五千億的發展之後，就變成這樣了
500 billion dollars a year later you get this!
這裡自帶裝逼表情的人還真多
There's a lot of smug-looking people in here huh!?
好像暴發戶白人都跑來了
It looks like someone just hit a pinata that was filled with white people who suck at golf
- 都從哪兒冒出來的？ - 別抱怨了，肯定很好玩
I mean, who are all these clown? -Ah come on, I think it looks fun!
查理，傑瑞德說咱們賺的是這些人的錢
Charlie, Vennett says these are the people we're betting against.
咱們過去，克里斯，到我左邊去，別擋道
Yeah, here we go Chris on my left, Chris, on my left!
- 大家好 - 什麼時候能見到你說的那些愛心天使
Gentlemen! -When do we get a chance to face-time with some of these lovely folks?
克里斯，把門卡發給他們
Chris, give em the key cards!
別弄混了
Do you even know which key-cords you're giving out?
- 先生們路上還順利嗎？ - 沒什麼事兒
First of all, how was your travel? -Uneventful?
- 沒事 - 我來了6小時了
Uneventful! -OK, I've been here for six hours!
我已經鍛煉完，吃了兩個荷包蛋 還和演員斯坦頓一起打牌
I've already been to the Gym, I had two poached eggs, and I played blackjack with Harry Dean Stanton
你記日記還真清楚
Thank you for your diary!
- 我想找人見面聊 - 提醒你們記住，我們是來收集信息的
Face-time! I'd like some face-time! -Just remember, we're here just to gather information!
我們是收集信息，不要打草驚蛇
We're gathering information, we're not advertising our short-position!
別嚇到大夥兒，行不行？
Right? We don't want to spook anybody! Can we do that?
你說話太直，還老是不停嘴
You got a big mouth, and you like to run it
- 這幾天能不能收斂一點？ - 好吧，好吧
Can you just keep it shut for a few days? -OK, OK!
別擔心，我們會好好套話的
Yeah, don't worry, we'll play nice!
女士們先生們
Ladies and gentlemen!
商業形勢大好
Business is good!
利潤也很高！
Profits are strong!
房貸還堅持著經濟的中流砥柱作用
and the mortgage continues to be the bedrock on which this economy is built.
去年我們在次級貸市場有些損失
Yes, we had to take some losses in our sub-prime department last year,
不過預計也就最多損失5%
But those losses, will be contained at only five percent!
接下來說
Now
我們住宅業務板塊的表現
In our residential sector...
馬克，這不是提問環節！
Mark, it's not a Q&A!
我們推出的可調利率房貸被一搶而空
our roll out of those variable rate-packages were gobbled up by the
我有個問題！
I have a question please!
先生，本來提問環節是在我陳述之後 但看你這麼著急
Sir, the Q&A is after my statement, but you know what, you seem anxious!
- 現在就問吧，你好啊 - 你好，謝謝！
How can I help you? -How are you? Fine, thank you!
你覺得…
Would you say,
有沒有這個可能性，或者說必然性
that is it a possibility, or a probability
次級貸的損失最多升到5%封頂？
that sub-prime losses stop at five percent?
謝謝！
Thank you!
我覺得這簡直是必然的，是的！
I would say it is a very strong probability, indeed!
再回到住宅部分
So, ehm, back to the residential sector,
- 我們推出可調利率… - 我還沒問完
when we rolled out the new variable rates package -Excuse me!
這位先生
The ehm. Yes Sir!
零！
Zero!
ZERO!
可能性為零
There is a zero percent chance
次級貸止損到5%的可能性為
that your sub-prime losses will stop at five percent!
零！
Zero!
抱歉！
Excuse me!
- 我得接這個電話了 - 你一定來自眼紅我們的美國銀行吧！
I have to take this -He must be from Bank of America!
我現在什麼都沒乾
No, I'm really not doing anything right now!
- 我正說到住宅部分 - 孩子們都還好嗎
as I was saying, our residential sector -uh huh, and how are the kids?
客戶對我們的房貸產品反響…
Consumers reacted to our packages
馬克真的這麼做了！他來拉斯維加斯真敢這麼做
Mark Baum really did that! when we were in Vegas he did that!
敢這麼說，還接電話走人了
He said that... he took the call,
明白我有多費心了嗎？
Now you see what i had to deal with!
這UZI微衝真是爽啊！
This Uzi is fucking awesome!
只要讓CDO再轉上兩年
If I can get this CDO-machine to run for another two years
我就能富的流油，在滑雪勝地買房了
and then, I'm rich as fuck and I got my house in Aspen!
你對證券化的資產表現不擔心嗎
But do you have any concerns about the performance of the underlying securitizations?
違約的消息一直有
It's easy to see that delinquencies,
斷供率又在增長了
eh, default-rates are on the rise right now!
你倆怎麼老潑冷水，有意思嗎
Could you please stop being such a buzz-kill dude!
帶你們來放鬆，不是再來聊工作的
We didn't bring you out here to talk about work bro!
你為什麼帶我們過來
Why'd you bring us out here?
因為我們必須讓客戶給彈藥買單
Because we need to be able to expense the ammo to a client!
來繼續射擊恐怖份子吧，你們看著點
We're gonna shoot some terrorists, watch out boys!
- 這是一群白痴！- 真是個棒槌！
These guys are morons! -Fucking tool!
真爽！
Woo!- Fuck Yes!
爽啊！炸啊！
Boom, yeah man BOOM!
- 我們所有餘錢都應該買互換！ - 先別急，別急
We ought to be buying every swap we can get our hands on! -Just hold on okay, hold on!
我哥哥的前女友在證券交易委員會工作 她說她也在城裡，我去聊聊
My brother's ex-girlfriend works for the SEC, she just told me she's in town, okay!?
如果有些內幕消息我們不知道 她是最有可能透露給我們的人
So if we're missing something, maybe she can tell me, give me some insight.
你這邊先去一樓再買點互換
In the mean-time, you go to the main floor to buy some more swaps
有個事兒，我們想要投資房貸證券
Well actually, we're about to invest in housing bonds.
我想問問證券交易委員會的態度
I was just wondering if the SEC is worried about them at all
我知道你不能透露具體內容 但你可以說說大概態度
I know you're not allowed to tell me specifics, but, just generally.
我們不去調查房產證券
Ow, we don't investigate mortgage bonds
實際上，我們預算減了以後 就不怎麼調查了
Truth is, since we had our budgets cut, we don't investigate much!
- 那你開會不是來調查的嗎？ - 我又不是以證交會員工身份過來的
Then why are you here? I thought.. -I'm not here for the SEC!
我自己花錢來的
I'm here on my own dime
正給各大銀行投簡歷呢
I'm floating my resume to some big banks!
你哥還好嗎？
How's your brother by the way?
你怎麼能把簡歷遞給大銀行呢？
How are you floating your resume to big banks?
你不是應該監管大銀行嗎？
I mean, you're supposed to be the ones policing the big banks
你幾歲了，傑米
Grow up Jamie!
肯定有法律規定你們不能…
There must be some kind of law against working for a financial institution
馬上從監管跳到被監管的地方
right after you've been working in financial regulation right?
沒有
No!
沒有啊
嘿
Hey!
道奇！
Dougie!
- 快過來！你怎麼也來凱撒宮了 - 他在高盛工作
Hey, come over here! What are you doing at Caesar's? -He's a Goldman
我們應該能做5%的3B評分互換
We can do BBB-level swaps at 500 basis points, maybe!
你們互換價格這麼高 好像證券要跌破價一樣
You're pricing the swaps, like the bond is gonna collapse
雖然現在證券價格還在上升？你確定嗎
Even though the bond-value is going up? Really?
- 這是變革的年代！ - 搞不懂究竟是怎麼回事啊
Exciting times! -What the hell is going on?!
劉易斯，你能明天早點兒過來嗎？
Lewis, Can you come early tomorrow, please?
我得減持美國國際集團 國家銀行、聯邦住房抵押貸款公司
I need to unload the AIG and Countrywide Freddie Mac positions
這樣才能填上資金缺口
so we can afford the premiums on the
核心做空的保費還差一些
core mortgage-shorts on the swaps
沒問題，貝利博士
No problem Dr. Burry
貝利博士！
Dr. Burry!
要是投資者撤資，咱們接下來會怎麼樣？
If the investors withdraw, what's gonna happen here?
我們就完了？
Are we done?
我也不知道
Honestly I don't know!
證…
The, the...
證券一直不下跌！
the bonds aren't going down!
一動不動！
They won't move!
很有可能
It's possible
整個金融系統都在欺詐
That we are in a completely fraudulent system.
或者…是你…錯了
Or... you're, you're wrong.
是有可能
Sure!
有這個可能，可我找不出我錯在哪裡
It's possible, I just don't know how!
我估計
I guess....
別人…
when...
犯了錯，也不知道
someone's wrong, they never..
錯在哪裡吧！
they never... Know how!
- 早上見吧！ - 好
See you in the morning! -Yeah.
貝爾也把價格提高了！
Even Bear up their prices!
管我們棕地基金叫屎洞基金
they keep calling us Brown Hole
你們沒錢沒名聲，他們瞧不起也正常 別往心裡去
you just don't have the money or the reputation, don't take it personal!
估計今晚我沒心情去看脫衣舞了，喝點酒去
I don't think i have the strip-club in me tonight I'm just gonna get some drinks around.
晚上看些付費A片，訂好明早的機票就行了
Watch some Pay-per-view book us some flights out for the morning.
交易…我們需要做成一筆交易
d- d- deal, we need a deal, right, a deal.
我們得做一個能承受的，並且對方肯定不會拒絕的
Uhm, we need a deal we can afford, we need a deal they're not gonna refuse!
怎麼辦呢…
So... What can we do? We can....
2A評級的怎麼樣？我們壓注2A評級的證券
The AA-tranches, What if we bet against the AA-tranches?
誰會拒絕這種賭注？
Who's not gonna take that bet?
他們說95%都是3A級別的
We know that they say they're ninety-five percent AAA-rated
其實頂多才有25%，剩下的都是垃圾證券
But in reality, they're more like twenty-five percent, some of them are zero percent!
我們也知道如果最差評級的證券 有超過8%作廢
We also know that if the bottom-tranches fail at over eight percent
就會導致最上面的證券也跟著雪崩
The upper-tranches are affected and they go to zero.
所以這些2A級別，頂多就是B級
I'll bet you right now, that those AA's are actually like B's!
我很少這麼說，不過這回查理是對的
I rarely ever say these words but i think Charlie is right!
你看，本
Look, Ben!
回報率…
Pay-off!
是200比1，但他們是根據現在評級來定價
is 200-to-1, but they're all taking the ratings of face value
所以低風險2A的保費很低
They're charging penny's on the dollar to bet against Double-A's
我剛開始覺得你倆是笨蛋
Just when i start thinking you guys are clowns!
地球人都不會去做空2A級別
No-one on the planet is betting against Double-A's
銀行會認為我們嗑藥了，或者中風了
The banks will think we're either high, or having a stroke
他們會大方接受我們的所有提議
And they'll take every dime we have to offer!
絕妙的主意
Kind of brilliant!
這個點子，只有我們想到了
This is what we did, that no-one else thought of.
連馬克和麥克都沒有做空2A
Not even Baum or Berry thought to short the Double-A's
但我們做了
But we did.
我們這個小不點屎洞基金
Little Brown Hole Capital
我們想做空一些2A級的CDO
So we're interesting in shorting some of the AA-tranches of CDO's
直說吧，你倆在打什麼主意？
Come on guys, what's the angle?
我們沒其他意思，新手嘛，很想拿這個試手！
I've got no angle, we're new to this, we're just so hyped!
我們想買1千5百萬互換，做空2A級
We wanna do fifteen million in swaps on the Double-A tranche
我是搞不懂你們
I don't understand!
你倆願意買多少就買多少
You can buy as much Double-A tranches as you want!
那就4千萬做空2A吧
Forty million against the Double-A
哥們，你願意買多少我都賣給你
Brother, I would sell you as much as you want!
我知道我在買啥，你想賣嗎？
I understand perfectly Bob! Want the deal?
好啊，我沒問題
That's cool, that's alright with me!
他走了
He's gone!
別這樣，快停下來
don't do that! Stop, Stop!
別鬧了！查理！
Stop that! -Charlie! Wooooh!
停下來，你倆！
Stop it, Stop!
怎麼了
What?
知道你們剛剛做了什麼事嗎
Do you have any idea what you just did?
我倆做成了一輩子一遇的買賣啊，應該慶祝
Come on, we just made the deal of our lifetime, we should celebrate!
你倆在賭未來美國經濟崩潰
You just bet against the American economy!
是啊！沒錯！
Fuck yeah we did! -Yeah!
- 這意味著 - 太棒了
Which means! Fuck yeah! OH!
這意味著，如果我們賭對了
Which means... If we're right....
如果我們是對的，人們會無家可歸
If we're right, people lose homes!
大批人會失業
people lose jobs!
大家沒了退休存款，養老錢都沒了！
People lose retirement savings, people lose pensions!
我最討厭這行的就是這一點 人不是數字！
You know what i hate about fucking banking! It reduces people to numbers!
那我告訴你，失業率上升1%
Here's a number! Every one percent unemployment goes up,
死亡人數會增加4萬人，明白嗎
40 thousand people die! Did you know that?!
- 知不知道？ - 不，我們不了解
Did you know that? -No, I didn't know that!
我們就是有點興奮
We were just excited!
還跳舞就太過分了
Just don't fucking dance!
好吧 你要去哪
Alright! -Where are you going?
我心裡有點發毛了
Whoah, I just got really scared!
今天表現挺好嘛
First of all, great show today!
簡直好極了
You were terrific!
- 謝謝  - 你嘴不嚴實還真是我出乎意料
Thank you! -Your big mouth was a revelation!
理解萬歲
I appreciate that!
你們擔心有人暗箱操作？
You worried you, and your swaps were getting played?
現在這個機會，讓你們去看看對手是誰
Well, this is an opportunity for you to meet who you're betting against!
別覺得自己正義，就不聽不進他的話
Try not to get too righteous and listen a little!
好吧，這人是誰？
OK, Fine! Who is this guy?
24K級的混蛋
A real solid-gold asshole!
我是CDO經理
I'm a CDO-manager
- 還有這個職位？ - 在哈丁顧問公司就有
A CDO-manager? -Yup, at Harding Advisors
我從沒想過CDO還有什麼要管的
I didn't realize that there was anything to manage with CDO's
不奇怪
Oh, well.
我們篩選進入CDO投資組合的證券 監控背後的資產情況
We select the securities that go into the CDO-portfolio and monitor the assets
我主要做美林證券的CDO
I do most of Merrill-Lynch's CDO's
你是代表投資人還是美林？
Do you represent the investors or Meryll-Lynch?
投資人啊！
The investors!
是嘛
You do.
可是…
Yeah! -But...
美林不可能白白送客戶給你
Meryll-Lynch isn't gonna send you any customer unless you put
除非你把美林也包含進CDO
Merrill-Lynch's bonds in your CDO....
問得好
Good question!
你可以假設…美林和我
Let's just assume Merrill and I have a...
我們關係不錯
we have a good relationship
你和美林證券關係不錯？
You have a good relationship with Merrill-Lynch?
我們一起做買賣
We've been doing business together
所以你選出的CDO
And so the CDO's..
這些CDO
that you create
都是最高品質的
are, are, are, of the highest quality
最有價值的
and the highest of value!
- 那是當然 - 那是當然…
Absolutely! -Absolutely!
你不擔心正在上升的斷供率嗎？
Are you at all concerned about the rising default-rates?
我個人不覺得CDO有風險
I assume no risk for this produce myself Mark
好吧
Okay!
那我直說吧
So let me get this straight
銀行聯繫你
The bank calls you up
讓你幫忙賣他們的證券
They give you the bonds they wanna sell
再送給你客戶，給你錢讓你運行公司
They give you clients, they give you money to run your business,
提成也少不了你的
Give you fat fee's for doing so
你居然還代表投資者？
but you represent the investors?
你是這個邏輯嗎？
Is that right?
是啊
Yeah!
但我不在美林大廈裡工作
But we're not in the Merrill-Lynch building!
- 那你在哪 - 我在新澤西
OK, where are you? -We're in New Jersey!
開車20分鐘就到了
You're twenty minutes away!
5分鐘就行了，如果你坐直升飛機
Five, if you use the helicopter!
挺好玩吧
That's funny eh?
真是好玩
That's hilarious!
不好
Oh boy!
你老闆要發作了
Your boss is about to explode!
他太想搞明白了，發作不了
No, he's too curious to explode!
等等，你再解釋一下
Hold on, say that again!
兩個CDO，A包含著B的一部分
CDO A, has parts of CDO B
然後B也包含A一部分，然後AB被放到C裡面
And CDO B, has parts of CDO A and then they both get put inside CDO C.
對，這就是CDO平方
Yeah and that one is called CDO square!
CDO的CDO
A CDO of a CDO!
明白？
Right?
CDO還能包含你互換押注剩下的部分
And then there's CDO's made up of the opposite sides of the bet you made with the swaps
我們叫它，合成CDO
We call them, synthetic CDO's
你說啥？合成CDO？真是亂套了
What did you just say? Synthetic CDO's? That is fucking crazy!
沒有亂，這很賺錢
It's not! It's awesome!
他臉都氣紅了，像槍戰遊戲裡的壞蛋
His face is starting to boil He looks like the bad guy from DOOM
那我們假設
Alright, let's say...
你有5千萬美元的次級貸
You have a pool of 50 million in sub-prime loans
那賭在上面的錢，能有多少？
How much money could be out there betting on it
在你的合成CDO和互換裡？就按今晚的行情
In your synthetic CDO's and swaps? right now! Tonight!
5千萬的次級貸…
50 million.. hmm..
10億美元吧
a billion dollars
啥？
What?
如果麥克最早發現的房貸證券是火柴的話
If the mortgage-bonds that Michael Burry discovered were the match...
房貸市場衍生出的證券規模有多大
How much bigger is the market for insuring mortgage bonds than for actual mortgages?
大概20倍吧
About twenty times!
如果房貸證券是火柴
If the mortgage bonds were the match...
那CDO就是煤油弄濕的破布
Then the CDO's were the kerosene soaked rags.
而合成CDO，就是原子彈
Then the synthetic CDO was the atomic bomb
啟動按鈕被一個酒鬼總統把持著
with a drunk president holding his finger over the button
這個時刻，在這破餐館
It was at that moment in that dumb restaurant
馬克表情像傻了一樣 他頭一次意識到
with that stupid look on his face that Mark Baum realized
整個世界經濟可能要崩潰了
The whole world economy might collapse!
我知道你們在想什麼
And i know what you're thinking!
合成CDO又是什麼鬼
What the fuck is a synthetic CDO?
* 塞勒博士 美國經濟學會主席 芝加哥大學教授 行為決策研究所所長 改變了經濟學家研究人類的方式 “行為經濟學”之父
* Richard H. Thaler
好，讓行為經濟學之父塞勒博士 和莎琳娜解釋一下
Well, here's Dr. Thaler, father of behavioral economics, and Selena Gomez to explain!
*莎琳娜，國際流行樂壇巨星
* Selena Gomez International Pop Star
合成CDO是這麼回事
Ok, so here's how a synthetic CDO works!
就說我賭1千萬在21點牌局的這手上
Let's say i bet ten million on a black jack hand.
1千萬，大概就是一個房貸證券的規模
Ten million, because this hand is to represent a single mortgage bond
好的，莎琳娜這手牌不錯
Okay, Selena has a pretty good hand here!
兩張明牌18點，莊家7點 莎琳娜拿到了一手好牌
showing eighteen, dealer showing seven That's a really good hand for Selena!
贏面大，實際這手牌贏的概率
Good odds, In fact her chances of winning this hand
是87%
are eighty-seven percent
就是說我很可能贏了
So, my odds are good
現在我勢頭正旺
I'm on a winning streak
大夥也想要趁勢賺錢
Everybody in this place wants to get in on the action
我怎麼會輸呢？
How could i lose right?
這是個經典的思維缺陷
Now this is a classic error
籃球裡面叫“熱手謬誤”
In basketball it's called the Hot-Hand-Fallacy
一個人連續投籃進了
A player makes a bunch of shots in a row
大夥會覺得下一次也會進
People are sure they're gonna make the next one
人們認為，發生過的事情
People think, whatever is happening now
在以後也會繼續出現
Is gonna continue to happen into the future!
在房地產泡沫時期
During the real-estate boom
房價一直在漲啊漲
Markets were going up and up!
人們會覺得房價不可能跌下來
and people thought they would never go down!
旁觀的人心想，賭邊注的話，也不會輸
People who are watching and think that I won't lose will make a side-bet
這就是第一個合成CDO
Now this, is the first synthetic CDO
我喜歡莎琳娜
I love Selena Gomez!
我和你賭1千5百萬，賭她贏
I'll bet you fifteen million, she wins!
賠率設3：1
And I'll give you 3-to-1 odds!
3：1？
3-to-1 odds?
好，我和你賭
Okay, I'll take that bet!
現在
Now!
旁邊還有人對他倆的賭局再對賭
somebody else is gonna wanna make a bet on the outcome of their bet!
1千五百萬賭她贏
15 million she wins!
形成了第二個合成CDO
That will lead to synthetic CDO number two!
我和你賭2億，賭那個戴眼鏡的女士贏
I bet you 200 million, that lady in the glasses, wins that bet!
她是贏面很大
She probably will win!
所以我很可能大賺一筆
So i want great pay-off!
我就來賠率20：1吧
How about 20-to-1?
成交
Deal!
這樣的過程循環往復 合成CDO越來越多
And this will go on and on, with more and more synthetic CDO's
原始的1千萬投資
And we can transform an original ten million dollar investment
滾雪球成為了幾十億的賭注
Into billions of dollars
你沒事吧
You're Ok?
不舒服
No!
我感覺很噁心
I actually feel pretty sick!
我得先走了
So I'm going to leave
馬克，你心裡認為我就是寄生蟲是吧
You think I'm a parasite don't you mister Baum?
可社會待見我這樣的人
But apparently society values me,
非常待見
very much.
不信的話，咱們算算
In fact, Let's do this!
我先告訴你
I'll tell you,
我現在身價多少
how much I'm worth.
你再告訴我你身價多少
You tell me how much you're worth!
你還真是個…
You are an incredibly...
渾身銅臭味的混蛋
big piece of shit!
買空他做的所有CDO，再投入5個億
Short everything that guy has touched, I want half a billion more in swaps
你確定嗎？萬一不行你就破產了
Sure about that? The collateral calls could bankrupt you!
我確定
Yeah!
你要去哪兒
Where are you going?
我得去輪盤賭那裡恢復一下粉碎的三觀
I am going to try to find moral redemption at the roulette table
情況比我設想的還要糟
Things are worse than I thought
這次我真覺得經濟要崩潰了
I honestly think the economy might collapse!
你這麼說都說了幾年了
You've been saying that the system is broken for years Mark
這次是怎麼了
Why are you so shocked?
我再挖空心思，也想不到裡面這麼黑
It's more twisted, than i could have imagined!
你總是對自己有很高的道德要求
You love to be the virtuous one
我做這行，在這個染缸裡
I'm a banker, I'm a part of it!
你總是這樣
You always have Mark!
- 不想沾染髒東西 - 我也被改變了，我也被改變了
Like you're untainted -It changed me, it changed me!
我變成了…
Into a person,
再也不能和別人交心的人
who is not able to reach out to someone
我兄弟當時很痛苦，真的很痛苦
He was in pain, my brother was in real pain!
沒有十全十美的辦法來幫他
There is no perfect way to help
難受就說出來
Say it, it's scary
停下來
So, Stop!
別想著拯救世界了
Trying to fix the world!
他對說我
He told me
你不是聖人，聖人不會住在公園大道的富人區裡
You're not a saint, saints don't live on Park Avenue!
那時他就有不好的想法
That he was having bad thoughts.
你得去接受自己的喜怒哀樂 像我們普通人一樣
Just feel the feelings, like the rest of us!
我當初怎麼幫他的…
My first response...
第一反應是給他錢
Was, to offer him some money.
我只會給錢！
I offered him fucking money!
他最後臉都摔爛了
His face was so smashed!
bgm 《By Demons Be Driven》by Pantera
*bgm: By Demons Be Driven, by Pantera
麥克
Michael?
- 麥克？ - 我在
Michael? -Yes, Yes!
- 你沒事吧？ - 沒事，親愛的
Is everything Ok? -Yes honey!
真的？
Sure?
寶貝放心吧
Yeah baby!
沒事了
All fine, hehe!
至所有的投資人，你們也知道
To all investors, as you may know,
我們的協議允許我，在市場運行脫軌的時候
Our agreement allows me, to take extraordinary measures
採取極端的措施
When markets aren't functioning properly
我現在有理由相信
I currently have reason to believe
房貸證券市場是個騙局
The mortgage-bond market is fraudulent
為了保護各位的投資不受扭曲市場的影響
So, in order to protect investors from this fraudulent market
我決定禁止投資者撤資
I've decided to restrict investor withdrawals
後續情況請等待通知
Until further notice.
真誠的，麥克·貝利博士
Sincerely, Dr. Michael J. Burry
*我要起訴你
* I'm suing.
*Facebook壯大
*Facebook grows
*2007年4月16日，弗吉尼亞理工大學校園槍擊案
*2007 Apr 16, Virginia Tech Shooting
其實，人人都在內心深處
*Everyone, deep in their hearts
企盼世界末日的到來
*is waiting for the end of the world to come.
村上春樹《1Q48》
*Haruki Murakami, 1Q84
天哪，夥計，你能不能…
Oh my god dude, would you...
別老是換頻道了
Please stop changing the channel
- 要把我逼瘋了 - 好吧
It's been driving me crazy! -Fine!
就放商業新聞好了，謝謝
Just put the business-news on please. Thank you!
標準普爾指數提升3點
And the S&P picked up three points
小題大做！（2007年4月2日）
Jesus!  (*2007.Apr.2)
房貸市場崩潰還在繼續
Mortgage Meltdown continues
曾經是領軍企業，發放次級貸的
sub-prime mortgage-lender New Century Financial
新世紀金融公司申請破產
Once the industry-leader by the way, filed for bankruptcy
該公司馬上…
The company immediately, Ahem!
我清一下嗓子 （電視：CNN 新世紀金融公司破產）
good time for my voice to go (*CNN New Century Bankrupt mortgage leander)
…裁員了3200人
Fired 3,200 workers
與三月相比，製造業指數仍在下滑
The manufacturing-index also fell off the month of march
開始了…
It's starting....
有專家提醒，經濟增長可能會放緩
A warning that the economic growth could slow
相關機構聲稱，次級貸資產價格仍在上漲
The institute of sub-prime assets also reported a rise of prices
我必須打電話給我媽了
I'm gonna call my mom!
*經濟放緩的主要原因
*The principle source of the slowdown of economic growth
每次我都幫你擋著，馬克
Time, and time, and time again I've brought you back, Mark
我們認識都17年了
We've know each-other for seventeen years
她嗓門這麼大，真是厲害
She 's got some lungs on her I'm impressed!
看她生氣我還挺高興
Can't help but enjoy it.
絕對不可能，大銀行哪有這麼蠢
There's no fucking way, there's no fucking way, that the big banks are that stupid!
再見 凱茜！
Bye Kathy!
怎麼說
Well?
凱茜說，我們應該賣掉做空的互換
Kathy thinks it would be a good idea if we sold our shorts
老話重提
What else is new?
她說摩根士丹利會買下來
And she said that Morgan-Stanley will buy them
我去！
Holy shit!
你怎麼說
What did you say?
我告訴她，我們啥都不賣
I told her we're not selling shit!
*貝爾斯登清算了兩家對沖基金 近期因次級貸損失慘重
*Bear Stearns Liquidates Two Hedge Funds After Massive Subprime Mortgage Losses
如果你需要2005年資料的話…
Ah, if you need the.. ehm, Files from 2005
菲爾德先生的訴訟，只需要去年到現在的資料
Mister Field's suit is very specific to files from the past year
那出去吧！代我向勞倫斯問好，向他倆都問好
Good, then get out! Say hi to Lawrence for me! and both do!
你一個禮拜都不能回我電話？
You can't call me back for a week?
我很抱歉，麥克
I'm so sorry Mike!
高盛的系統崩潰，我把很多消息都丟了
Goldman had a systems failure i lost a ton of messages!
美國銀行說他們停電了 摩根士丹利說服務器崩潰了
B of A said they had a power outage, And Morgan-Stanley said their server crashed!
這麼湊巧！
That's weird!
我覺得不太可能
Meh, I will, I will call it, improbable
那你記錄我們的資金量是多少
Where do you have our position marked?
和以前一樣，麥克
I think it's the same Mike
什麼？你能給我解釋一下嗎？
What? Can you explain that to me please?
被保的東西都毀滅了還不能用保險
H-H-H How can the value of an insurance-contract
那一個保險合同還叫什麼保險合同？
Not be affected by the demise of the very thing it insures?
他們是獨立的市場，兩者並不總是相關
They're independent markets, They're not always correlated!
我知道聽起來奇怪 但是它們都是十分複雜的金融產品
I know it sounds odd, but these are very complicated products!
它們本來就是相關的
They ARE correlated!
人們會沒了房子，丟了工作，養老金…
They're gonna lose their houses, They're gonna lose their jobs, They're gonna lose their p..
*發件人:貝爾斯登，報價和上次一樣
* Bear Stearns, Bid and ask are the same as last time. No change.
你好好聽我說！
Will you listen to me!
這次…就像資本主義終結一樣嚴重
This is like.... The end of capitalism!
再次回到黑暗時代
This is like the dark ages all-over again!
我不想和我爸說話！ 我也愛你，把你們的錢保護好！
I don't want to talk to dad! Okay, I love you too, save your money!
她說我得去開治抑鬱的藥 抗焦慮的藥要加倍
She says I need to be on Xanax, and double my dose of Zoloft
我問貝爾斯登買我們做空的報價 他們說CDO價格還是沒變
I asked Bear-Stearns to price our shorts They tell me the CDO's still haven't moved
這幫人真是喪心病狂了
This is fucking insane!
這幫合夥騙子，應該進監獄！
You realize that? These people are crooks and they should be in prison!
看看資產擔保證券指數 CDO的價值已經是零了
Look at the ABX, you can see that the CDO's are worth zero!
你知道他們想幹啥嗎
So you know what they're doing huh?
You know what they're doing right? -Yeah!
他們之所以不買
They're not loading them...
是因為要賣出去自己的狗屎CDO
They're selling their dogshit CDO's
然後才能去另一家銀行
Then they go to another bank
- 做空自己的狗屎，再吃進去！ - 天哪，咱們可以去找媒體了
And short the shit, while they fucking sold it! -Whoo ho ho, Let's go to the press man!
這絕對是轟動新聞！誰會不願意登
This is a massive story! Who wouldn't publish it?
羅伯特·雷德福那樣的！ （*在《總統班底》中，羅伯特扮演的記者 在巨大壓力下查出了水門事件的真相）
Robert Redford!
- …再做空自己買下的 - 我明白了，我明白了
shorting the ones they buy -I got it, I got it!
我明白了 （*華爾街日報 紐約美洲大道1211號）
I got it, I got it... (*Wall Street Journal, 1211 Avenue of the Americas)
我又能做什麼？ （*華爾街日報 紐約美洲大道1211號）
And what am I supposed to do? (*Wall Street Journal, 1211 Avenue of the Americas)
難道寫一篇報道，題目就叫“我們都完蛋了”
Want me to write a piece called: "We're all fucked!"
好啊，完美的題目
Yes! That's a perfect title!
現在所有的銀行都在轉手這些垃圾證券
Right now, every bank in town is unloading these shit-bonds
讓那些不了解內情的人買單
under un-suspecting customers
他們在賣出去之前是不會主動降價的
and they won't devalue them until they get them off their books
這種犯罪程度在華爾街也是史無前例！
This level of criminality is unprecedented even on fucking Wall-street!
傑米
Jamie...
我就坦誠的和你說吧
This is me being honest here okay.
我在華爾街建立關係網花了好幾年
It took me years to build my relationships on Wall-street
沒有銀行或者評級機構…
No bank or ratings-agency
會傻到主動承認你倆所說的
Is gonna confirm a story like this
你倆的基金開在車庫
just because it comes from two guys in a...
吵吵著世界末日就要來了，誰信
garage-band hedge-fund that thinks it's the apocalypse.
我還以為你是良心記者 真的，我一直都這麼想
I thought you were for real Kathy You know, I have to say, I really did!
傑米，你和我講良心，我現在小孩3歲
Yeah Jamie, you try being for real with a three-year old
老婆也要交學費讀碩士
and a wife getting her masters-degree
我不會因為你們瞎猜就把自己的名譽賠進去
I'm not gonna burn my reputation on your wild hunch
麻煩你倆跑一趟了，見到你們真開心
Thanks for coming guys, totally fucking awesome to see you!
我們也是，之前我就對你不爽
Yeah. I, Kathy I, I, I've always hated you
在大學裡面你就這臭屁樣兒 到現在了還是沒改
Because you were a prick in college and you are a prick today!
謝謝評價，那你還在和你媽一起住嗎？
Thanks Charlie! Still living with your mom?
查理，咱們走
Charlie, Come on!
我是馬克·鮑姆，給我回電話！
It's Mark Baum again. Call me!
次級貸證券大跳水
Sub-prime bonds fell off a cliff
傳聞有大批房貸斷供
Rumor has it default-numbers are huge!
誰先拿到匯款數據了？估計是高盛
Who got the remittance data early? I bet it's Goldman
真是幫倒忙
Nah, Fuck you very much!
傑瑞德，我這兒一團亂麻，咱們情況怎麼樣
Jared! It's chaos down here, where are we?
“他哭泣了，再也沒能讓我征服的地方了” （*亞歷山大大帝名言）
he wept for there are no more worlds to conquer
夏恩…
Shane...
夏恩！
Shane!
情況是
Well...
沒人買CDO和房貸證券了
Nobody's buying CDO's and mortgage bonds anymore
人人都要買互換，這是華爾街現在最搶手的東西
And everybody wants swaps, swaps are now the most popular product on the street
- 對我們是好消息吧！ - 是也不是
That's good for us! -Yes, and no.
我聽別人說…對方也從別處聽說…
I heard from somebody, who heard from somebody
不行，亞歷克斯，這裡我占了
No Alex. No..... Sorry!
我聽說摩根的本尼在證券部門損失慘重
Bennie Kreeger over at Morgan is taking up some heavy losses in the bond-department
（國家銀行因艱難處境發出金融預警）
*Countrywide Financial Warns of "Difficult Conditions."
你所在的大船可能漏水了
Your shit might be taking on water
趕緊穿上救生衣跳船吧
Time to get our life-jacket and get out.
我的天
holy shit!
我就...！
I'm jacked
我就...
I'm Jacked!
好爽
I'm jacked to the tits!
很好
Good!
- 能體會到痛苦又興奮的感覺嗎 - 我可不想
Do you feel it? -No!
你聽到什麼了泰德
What'd you hear Ted?
開始了
It's happening
大夥都要買我們的互換
Everybody wants our swaps
凱茜讓你去她辦公室
Kathy's office is looking for you!
黑臉的又變白臉了
Singing a different tune now, aren't they?
情況不妙啊
That's not good.
以後再說吧
Maybe later.
- 我沒開玩笑 - 你得開始脫身了
No, no this isn't a joke -you gotta start unwinding...
*高盛來電
* Goldman calling
我聽著呢
Listening!
- 貝利博士？ - 是我
Dr. Burry? -Yah!
我是高盛的迪伯·溫斯頓
Deeb Winston, Goldman Sachs
我看了一下你的價位
Listen, I've been reviewing your position
想要和你討論估值的情況，盡可能的公平
I wanted to discuss your marks, make sure they're fair!
我想…你的意思是
Yeah, I, I, I thi, I think you mean.. That you've..
你已經做空了自己的倉位 這樣你總算能認真評估我的互換了
secured a net-short position yourselves, so you're free to mark my swaps accurately for once
現在對你們也有利
Because it's now in your interest to do so.
我…我不知道你要我怎麼說
Ehm... I'm not sure what you want me to say
我想…
I think that....
你該說的都說了
I think you've already said it.
你告訴高盛的傑夫，我絕對不會轉移基金 太扯淡了
You tell Jeff at Goldman that I'm not transferring funds, this is bullshit!
回頭再說
Okay, we'll talk later.
謝謝…
thank you...
謝謝你這麼快就過來了
Thanks for coming so quickly Mark -Yeah
我知道你聽說了摩根有一些損失
I know you've been hearing rumblings about some losses Morgan has suffered.
- 恭喜你 - 恭喜什麼？
-Congratulations On what?
噢
Oh!
* 吸奶器，凱茜已經懷孕了
* Breast pump, indicating pregnant
謝謝
Thanks.
感覺挺好的吧
Ehm.. -Having fun?
還行！
Yes!  He he!
是感覺不錯
Tons!, Ehm....
我想告訴你
I just wanted you to know that ehm...
摩根是遭受了一些損失 但我們的流動資產還是很穩健
Yes, Morgan has suffered some losses, but our liquidity is strong,
不需要再擔心什麼了
And there's no cause for concern!
那需要擔心本尼嗎？
Would Bennie Kreeger be concerned?
聽人說他損失慘重
Because word on the street is he took some pretty heavy losses
凱茜，別遮掩了，咱們都認識多少年了…
Kathy come on, we know each-other.. What's going on?
說吧…情況有多嚴重
How..how..how bad is this?
好吧
Ok...
在兩年以前，摩根證券部門的克裡格 也開始做空次級貸
Two years ago, Bennie Kreeger in Morgan's bond-department also started shorting sub-prime housing
- 20億做空3B級 - 本尼比我想的還要聰明啊
Two billion in Triple-B's -Benny is smarter than i thought!
不，他一點也不聰明
No, he's not smart at all!
交的保費搭進去了其他利潤
The premiums on the swaps ate into his desks profit
為了保住3B的做空
To cover his Triple-B shorts,
他賣了很多的A和2A的交換做保護，很多！
He sold a lot of A- and Double-A swaps as protection, A lot!
他覺得，不可能A級的也會受影響
He believed that there was no way, that they could be affected.
你該不會說是摩根士丹利賣給我們交換的吧
Tell me Morgan-Stanley doesn't hold the contracts on these swaps
我的天
Holy shit
我一直都在找我們的對家是誰
All this time I've been trying to figure out whom I've been betting against.
沒想到是我們的母公司
And it's Morgan-Stanley
遭殃的是自己的公司
Which is me....
風險敞口有多少？30億？
What's your exposure? Three billion?
不可能超過40億吧？
Please don't tell me it's more than four!
我不能回答你這問題
I can't answer that!
你可以說…
Yes you can answer that, because...
我過來的時候，看到走廊上的人都在哭
I walk in here and people are crying in your hallway
凱茜
Kathy..
你跟我說什麼事兒都好 可什麼事兒現在都不好！
You bring me in to tell me everything is fine, and everything is not fine!
究竟現在是怎麼了
What? What is happening?
做多的敞口有…
Long exposure is...
150億
fifteen billion
- 我的老天爺，你在開玩笑吧！ - 你總是說斷供率不可能超過8%的！
Jesus Christ, are you fucking kidding me?! -You kept saying defaults over eight percent were impossible!
- 那樣會有1百萬人無家可歸 - 我的天
-That there would be a million homeless Oh my god!
摩根和我們沒有關係
Yeah, but we have nothing to do with Morgan-Stanley
那你上破產法庭這麼說去
Yeah... Just tell the bankruptcy-court
摩根破產，我們所有的錢都會轉到 他們的資產負債表上
Morgan fails, all our accounts go on their balance sheet
這也太瘋狂了
That's just crazy!
摩根輸了爛賭注，卻讓我們來還賬？
Morgan makes a sucker's bet and we pay their fucking gambling debt?
- 做空摩根的股票！
Short the bank's stocks! -Wait..
或者等市場一開始交易，就賣了我們的互換
Or we sell our swaps, when the market opens
我們拿到獎金，我們的投資人拿到收益
We get our bonuses, our investors get their profit
咱們能拿到一塊錢裡的三毛錢 至少能保命
We get... thirty cents on the dollar, Not bad!
我們比這值3倍
We're three times that
要是買家市場都沒了，就爛到手裡了
Not if there's no market up to sell them in
不行，我不能把救生船送給這些人
Forget it, I'm not giving any lifeboats
馬克，如果摩根垮了，到頭來我們什麼都沒有了
Mark, if Morgan goes under, we end up with nothing!
文尼
Vinnie...
別爭了
Jesus, come on!
我說賣，咱們再賣
I say, when we sell
我知道你跟華爾街有私人恩怨
Look I get that this is personal for you,
- 但是我們對投資人也要負責 - 我們不需要負責
But we have a fiduciary responsibility -No, no we don't!
我們負責？這裡誰給別人負責？
Respons..? Nobody is acting responsible!
責任！跟我談負責
Fuck responsibility! Are you kidding me?
大銀行的那些混蛋們，回頭能…
The assholes at the big banks, are gonna take..
- 你們點菜嗎？ - 我們在說正經事…別打擾
You boys want menu's now? -We're talking!.. Please!
抱歉了
Excuse us!
我們要等著，耐心等著
We are going to wait, and we are going to wait
等到他們知道疼了，開始流血了才行
We are going to wait, until they feel the pain, until they start to bleed
這才是我想要的結果
That is what I want
那我們的客戶怎麼辦 我們在拿他們的錢冒風險
Yeah, but what about our clients, they've been trusting us with their savings.
我說賣，我們再出手
I say when we sell!
這不是你公報私仇的時候
This isn't about you!
我說賣，再出手！
Hey, hey, HEY! I say when we sell!
好吧，那聽你的
Whatever you say Mark
夥計你看新聞了嗎
Dude, did you hear the news?
兩個貝爾投資的房貸對沖基金爆倉了
Ok, so not only did two mortgage hedge-funds backed by Bear-Stearns go belly-up
而且現在貝爾還被集體訴訟
but now, there's a class-action lawsuit against Bear
壞了
Holy shit!
跟我做！用力！用力！
Let's go! Push, Push!
- 那怎麼了？貝爾會破產嗎？ - 我們不能冒這個險
So? What? Bear could really collapse here? -That's a risk we really shouldn't take!
我們有80%的互換，是從貝爾那裡買的
But eighty percent of our swaps is Bear
我們可能陪個精光
We lose everything!
- 先生！- 馬上就好
Hey Sir! -One second!
- 這是我的看法 - 我們買了這東西，卻不知道怎麼賣
That's my opinion! -Aw, we bought these fucking things, and we have no clue how to sell them
是啊，所以我們得找本幫忙
I know, we have to get Ben to do it!
我一直給他打電話，他也不回
I've been trying to call him, but he won't get back to me
現在他和老婆一家人在度假，在英國！
No, he's on vacation with his wife's family! They're in England!
什麼？
What?!
* 黑馬酒吧，英國南部港口艾克斯茅斯
* The Black Horse Pub, Exmouth England
（本：現在出手還太早）
* too soon for that
本，你能聽清嗎
Hello, Ben? Hey!
- 你們好 - 我們在，你能聽清嗎
Guys? -Yeah, we're here, can you hear us?
我聽的清楚
Guys?- We hear ya, Yeah!
我這裡電話和網絡信號都不好
I probably got cell-phone and WiFi-service
居然要這樣賣掉2億的證券
I'm trying to sell 200 million dollars worth of securities
就在這酒吧
In a pub...
聞著綿羊味兒
smells like sheep
你能行的
You can do this!
我不想給你壓力 但你搞不定的話，我們就全賠光了
I don't want to pressure you Ben, but if you don't pull this off, we lose everything!
看看瑞士瑞信銀行的胃口如何
Ok, let's see what Credit Suisse's appetite is.
我是棕地基金，我想要拋售我的信用違約互換
This is Brownfield Fund, I'm wanting to unload my credit default swaps.
好的，你們有多少
Alright, what've you got?
大概有20個2A級別的CDO
Twenty Double-A tranches of CDO's
好吧…這些現在行情不太好
Eh yes.. but these eh... these are pretty bad
是啊，全是垃圾
Absolutely, they're complete shit!
- 你的… - 面值是2億50萬
What's your.. what's your? - Face-value is 205 million
美元
Dollars
那我們能…以40收購
Alright, we could, we could go to forty
不行，至少要1億
No, we want at least a hundred million
1個億？
A hundred million?
你是毒品販子，還是搞銀行的？
Who are you a drug-dealer or a banker?
你要是銀行家，就立馬給我滾蛋
Cause if you're a banker you can fuck right off!
我不知道能不能坐莊，直接說你的最好報價
I don't know if we can make a market, just give me your best price!
哎呦！1個億還嫌不夠
Yeah, Check! a hundred million worth, and aim higher!
我覺得我們期望差太多
I think we're far apart
你要是不想買，就直接掛斷
Look if you don't want to deal, just hang up.
跟我料想的一樣
That's what I thought!
9千萬
Ninety million
7千萬
Seventy!
8千5百萬
Eighty-five
- 7千8百萬 - 8千4百萬
Seventy-eight -Eighty-four!
我是貝利博士
It's Dr. Burry
看來金融危機馬上來了 （*全國斷供率超過12%）
Looks like the collapse of the financial sector is imminent (*national default rates above 12 percent)
我以現在的倉位出手
Start to sell my position
23億
2.3 billion
當然，我可以等著
Sure, I'll hold!
* 親愛的勞倫斯
* Dear Lawrence
* 你在賽恩資本的總盈利為4.89億
* Your profits totaling 489 million from Scion Capital
* 已經轉存到你的賬戶了
* have been deposited into your account
* 不用謝。
*You're welcome.
* 德意志銀行紐約分行, 4千7百萬
*Deutsche bank new york. 47 million
最終我還是對的
So I was right.
我被人噴了兩年…
I took a rash of shit for two years. But...
但是我是對的
I was right! And...
所有人都錯了！
Everyone was wrong!
我還拿到了獎金支票
And yeah i got a bonus-cheque for it
來告我啊
Sue me!
隨便了
You know.
這錢是不少，我能感到你們心裡有看法
It's a lot of money! I get it, I can feel you judging me.
很明顯嘛
That's palpable
可是呢
But hey!
我從沒說過我是這個故事裡的英雄人物
I never said I was the hero of this story
你好啊
Hey, hey babe!
情況怎麼樣？
How are we looking?
…八…萬
...ace... goi..
什麼？
S-Sorry?
- 是8千萬 - 8千萬成交了
No, eighty million! -Ok, so eighty million!
8千萬，8千萬，這挺好的是吧
Eighty million, eigthy million, that's good right?
8千萬很好，謝謝你，非常感謝！
Eighty is great, eighty is great, thank you, thank you so much!
錢都匯到瑞士聯合銀行了
Most of them went to UBS
你們運氣相當不錯
You're very lucky!
今天法國把國內最大的貨幣市場賬戶凍結了
The largest bank in France froze it's customer's money-market accounts today
風暴已經傳到歐洲了
This thing is hitting Europe!
希臘和愛爾蘭已經完了
Greece and Iceland are finished
西班牙正在遭殃
Spain is teetering
真的假的？這麼嚴重
Are you serious? Fuck!
本，等你回家給我們打電話
Ben call us when you get home!
不過放電話之前請等一下
But hey, before you go... I'm just wondering...
我一直想問…
Uhm..
你為什麼要和我們做這件事
Why did you do this with us?
你並不需要…當然我們很感謝你…但
You didn't have to, and eh.. you know, thank you, but, eh....
為什麼
Why?
你們說想要發財，現在你們有錢了
You guys said you wanted to get rich! -Now you're rich!
* 2008年3月14日
* 2008 March 14
房產和銀行還在持續出血 只有一家大單做空的還拒絕出售
As the housing-markets and banks continues to hemorrhage, only one of the big shorts refused to sell.
馬克·鮑姆的空頭（演講人 格林·斯潘）
*Keynote Speaker Alan Greenspan Mark Baum
這簡直比咱們導演的還要好 他在會議上和布魯斯·米勒同台討論
So it was beyond perfect, when he was asked to speak at a conference opposite Bruce Miller
著名的樂觀投資人
Famous bullish investor
他和馬克辯論以後
After he and Mark had their debate
格林斯潘，整個金融危機的總設計師 還要繼續講話
Alan Greenspan, one of the architects of the whole crisis, was scheduled to speak
馬克辦公室的人都來了 把朋友也邀請過來了
Everyone in Mark's office showed up, even invited friends!
這就像金融界的阿里和福爾曼的拳擊世紀對決
This... was the Ali versus Foreman of the financial world
現實主義者對戰傻瓜
Realists versus the fools
在我們以為事情不可能更完美的時候 你敢相信…
And if it seems almost too perfect... trust me!
這事兒發生了！
This happened!
歡迎大家的光臨
Welcome everyone!
* 貝爾股價 47
* Bear at 47
請讓我們熱烈歡迎
Please... Give a generous welcome to...
布魯斯·米勒和馬克·鮑姆
Mister Bruce Miller.... and Mark Baum
系好安全帶看戲了！
Strap yourself in!
你們有些人可能知道 貝爾斯登剛剛接受了一筆摩根的貸款
So as some of you may know, Bear-Stearns has just received a loan from J.P. Morgan
當然我們等些時間才能看到市場的反饋
Of course we gonna have to wait to see how the markets react
但這事本身就能打消對貝爾銀行的擔心了
But that should lay to rest any concerns about the bank self!
我理解，所以你本人不會出售你的2億股票了
No, I take it, you have no plans to sell your two-hundred million in Bear stock
當然不，實際上等我們聊完 我還要再買進更多
No, as a matter of fact, when we're done here, I'll probably go buy some more!
而對立觀點…馬克·鮑姆
For the opposing view... Mister Baum
我得站起來說
I gotta stand for this
好的，大家好
Okay, Hi!
我們公司投資理念很簡單
My firm's thesis is pretty simple
華爾街把最初劉易斯房貸證券的好點子
Wall-street took a good idea: Lewis Raneiri's mortgage-bonds
變成了一個欺詐和愚蠢做成的原子彈
And turned it into an atomic bomb of fraud and stupidity
現在原子彈馬上就要毀滅全球經濟了
That's on it's way to decimating the world economy
你說的還挺像那麼回事似的
How do you really feel?
我沒想到你現在還能笑的出來 我要是你的話可不這麼樂觀
I'm glad you still have a sense of humor! I wouldn't if I were you!
認識我的人都知道
Now, Anyone who knows me, knows..
我是對別人的錯誤直言不諱的
That I have no problem telling someone they're wrong.
（2008年3月14, 貝爾股票41點，39點）
*(2008 Mar 14) Bear at 41, Bear at 39
你快看，股價還在往下泄
It's a disaster, it just says here
- 但這一輩子，我是頭一次… - 我的天
But for the first time.. in my life.. -Holy fuck!
…真心笑不出來
It's not so enjoyable
現在的美國充斥著欺詐
We live in an era of fraud in America
不僅是銀行，連政府也參與其中
Not just in banking, but in government
教育，宗教
Education, religion
視頻，連棒球都作假
Food, even baseball
真正讓我擔心的
What bothers me...
並不是說欺詐不道德
Isn't that .. fraud is not nice
也不是說欺詐很邪惡
Or that fraud... is mean
而是說，在過去一萬五千年的歷史中
It's that .. for fifteen thousand years
欺詐和短視就從來沒有成功過
Fraud and short-sighted thinking have never ever worked
* 貝爾股價 37
* Bear at 37
- 一次都沒有 - 天哪
Not once, eventually -Jesus
- 總會失敗 - 已經降到37了
You'll get caught -We're at thirty-seven
- 行情要下跌了 - 這哪是下跌，這是暴跌
Things go south! -It's fucking plummeting man, it's fucking plummeting!
我們難道都忘記教訓了嗎？
When the hell did we forget all that?
我還以為我們有希望，真的這麼以為過
I thought we were better than this, I really did
還有
And..
雖然我們不夠明智 但是我也不覺得自己多麼正義，多麼驕傲
The fact that we're not, doesn't make me feel all-right and superior!
我只是為大家感到…深深的悲哀
It makes me feel... Sad.
- 我每次刷新，股價都在掉 - 垮掉算了
Everytime i fucking hit refresh it's dropping man -And hope it does goes down!
* 貝爾股價 35
*(Bear at 35)
看笑話的心情…
And as fun as it is to watch..
看這些自大愚蠢的華爾街人士大錯特錯
Pompous dumb Wall-streeters be wildly wrong
您也一樣，大錯特錯！
And you are wrong sir!
我只知道，最後…
I just know that at the end of the day
將是普通百姓來承受這些痛苦
Average people are going to be the ones, that are going to have to pay for all of this.
- 興亡總是百姓遭殃 - 32點
Because they always, always do! -Thirty-two?
- 真是32點 - 這是跌破的節奏
Shit! It's thirty-two -Yeah it's fucking tanked man
這是我的拙見，謝謝大家
That's my two cents, thank you!
我得去德意志銀行去看熱鬧
I'm gonna drop a deuce at Deutsche
我們的樂觀派有什麼回應嗎
Does our bull have a response?
在華爾街的整個歷史上
Only that in the entire history of Wall-street,
從沒有投資銀行失敗，除非因為犯罪被牽連
No investment-bank has ever failed, unless caught in criminal activities.
我的回應是堅持！我認為貝爾前景光明
So, yes! I stand by my Bear-Stearns optimism.
米勒先生，打擾了！一個小問題
Mister Miller, I'm sorry! quick question!
剛才你們正在談話的時候 貝爾的股票已經跌落了38%
From the time you guys started talking, Bear-Stearns' stock is falling more than thirty-eight percent
你還要再買入嗎？
Would you still buy more?
當然
Yeah, sure!
我當然要買入，為什麼不買
Of course i'd buy more, why not?
當場打臉
Boom!
- 天哪 - 糟了 - 我們第一部分的討論就結束了
Jesus Christ! - Oh no! That concludes the first part of our presentation
下面我們有請，傳奇的前美聯儲主席 格林斯潘
Up next, we have the legendary, former, chairman of the FED, Alan Greenspan!
大夥
Folks!
* 貝爾斯登和國家銀行先後破產 * 現在輪到雷曼兄弟了
* First Bear Stearns collapses, then Countrywide. * Now Lehman Brothers
- …雷曼兄弟的員工… - 華爾街的大公司股票跌到零
... employees of Lehmann Brothers today, -as the Wall-street giant's stock went to zero!
紐約銀行的形象毀於一旦
the collapse of the venerable New York Bank
之後將是幾個月的市場動盪 （2008年9月15日）
Follows a tumultuous few months of market volatility * 2008 Sep 15
我們擔心世界經濟…
and fear for the world economy...
我得去裡面看看
I gotta see inside
怎麼進去？
How?
來吧
Come on
我電話忘到辦公室了，門卡也扔了
I left my phone in the office, I threw my pass out already,
- 能用你的嗎？ - 愛用就用，我才不管
Do you mind if i take your pass? Borrow it? I don't give a shit anymore, you can do what you want!
* 雷曼兄弟
* Lehman Brothers
- 直接上班車，別對媒體說話 - 18年了，我就落了這麼個結果
Go directly to your transportation, do not talk to the press! -So that's it? After eighteen years!
還趕我走，我願意怎麼幹就怎麼幹
Go directly to your transportation, do not talk to the press! -I just leave? That's just fucking great, I can talk to whomever the hell I want!
別對媒體說話
Do not talk to the press!
直接上班車，別對…
Go directly to your transportation, do not talk to the
晚上想一起吃個飯嗎？
Hey look, you want to get a bit tonight? There's this ehm...
下東城那邊開了古巴餐館，可以去…
This new Cuban place just opened at the Lower East Side, so I suppose we could..
- 是嗎 - 是啊
Ah really? -Yeah!
咱們倆
You and I?
- 也帶上大夥吧 - 好主意
Yeah and eh.. other people -That sounds nice!
- 我很想去，謝謝你邀請我 - 總算打電話了
Yeah, I would like that, thank you very much! -Finally!
馬克
Mark, Hey!
這裡已經血流成河了
It's a bloodbath up here
摩根股票貶值一半，跌到23，10
Morgan's stock has lost half its value, it's down to 23,10
這是跌破的趨勢，我想和你談談脫身的事
It's in a free-fall decline, so I wanted to talk to you about pulling their money
現在不把錢撤出來就沒機會了
I mean... It's now or never Mark!
我們要出手了！
We gotta sell!
馬克！
Mark!
馬克，你聽到了嗎
Mark, do you hear me?
語音信箱1，您有15條留言
Mailbox #1, You have fifteen messages.
麥克我聯繫不上你 你能方便的時候盡快回電話嗎
Mike I can't seem to get a hold of you, could you please call me at your earliest convenience?
我是傑夫，你現在還要買股票？
It's Jeff, I.. eh.. You're buying stocks?
現在是股市最低點，你太離譜了
The market is at an all-time low, this is crazy!
我和我妻子是在網上認識的
I met my wife on Match.com
我的交友資料說我是個醫學院學生 只有一隻眼能用
My profile said that I'm a medical student with only one eye
不懂社交
An awkward social manner,
助學貸款還有14.5萬要還
and 145 thousand dollars in student loans
她的回信是
She wrote back...
我找的就是你這樣的
You're just what I've been looking for!
她的意思是我很坦誠 那我也對你們開誠布公
She meant honest, so let me be honest...
房地產危機是金融史上最大的機會
The housing-crisis represents the greatest financial opportunity
但賺錢並不像我想象的那樣簡單
Making money is not like i thought it would be.
做交易…殺死了生命中對我最重要的那部分 這部分和做交易無關
This business... Kills the part of life that is essential! The part, that has nothing to do with business
在過去兩年，我內心感覺到，黑暗的東西在自我吞噬
For the past two years, my insides have felt, like they're eating themselves.
我曾經尊敬過的人
All the people I respected,
現在再也不理我了
won't talk to me anymore
除了通過律師來找我
Except through lawyers.
人們…
People...
總希望有權威來告訴他們如何來選擇價值 但他們選擇權威
Want an authority to tell them how to value things, but they chose this authority
並不是基於事實情況，或者成就
not based on facts or... results
他們這樣選，只是因為這些人看起來很權威 說出了他們想聽的話
They chose it because it seems authoritative...and familiar!
可是…
And...
我從未盲從過大眾
I'm not, and never have been.... familiar
所以…
So..
我得到了嚴肅的結論，我必須關閉基金
So I've come to the solemn realization that I must close down the fund
真誠的，麥克·貝利博士
Sincerely, Michael J. Burry MD.
* 盈利489% 賽恩淨值
*489% SCION VALUE
* 總盈利 26.9億
* TOTAL PROFIT  2.69 Billion
這和我想象的不一樣
This isn't how I pictured it
- 你以為是什麼樣的 - 反正不是這樣
What do you think you'd find? -I don't know
人人都做個成年人
Grown-ups
馬克，你聽著嗎
Mark, are you there?
馬克
Mark?
財政部長和美聯儲主席剛剛離開白宮
Paulson and Bernanke just left the White House.
可能政府要出手了
There's going to be a bail-out
不出手不行啊
Well, they had to!
是吧
Right?
- 我們用擔保兌付房貸 - 這些人早就知道
We paid for mortgages with collaterals -They knew!
ATM機回頭會取不出錢來的 他們必須阻止這種情況發生
Cash would have stopped coming out the ATM, they had to back-stop this
這些銀行家知道政府會用納稅人的錢保他們 他們不是愚蠢，他們只是不在乎
They knew the tax-payers would bail them out, they weren't stupid, they just didn't care!
是啊，一幫騙子
Yeah, 'cause they're fucking crooks!
但是走著瞧吧，肯定會有人進監獄的
But, at lest we're gonna see some of them go to jail.
是吧？
Right?
大銀行會被拆分
We need to gonna have to break up the banks
- 不可能再為所欲為 - 我不知道，我不知道
The party is over! -I don't know, I don't know...
我總覺得，幾年之內 人們還是會和以前經濟危機一樣
I have a feeling, that in a few years, people are gonna doing, what they always do when the economy tanks.
責怪移民和窮人拖累了他們
They will be blaming immigrants and poor people.
但是馬克錯了！
But Mark was wrong!
接下來的幾年，幾百個銀行和評級高管進了監獄
In the years that followed, hundreds of bankers and rating-agency's executives went to jail.
證券交易委員會被政府徹查
The SEC was completely overhauled
議會也迫於壓力不得不拆分大銀行
and congress had no choice, but to break up the big banks
進一步規範房貸和金融衍生品市場
and regulate the mortgage and derivative industries
上面開玩笑啦！
Just kidding!
銀行把人們投資的錢拿走
Banks took the money the American people gave them
用來給他們自己開巨額獎金
and used it to pay themselves huge bonuses
然後賄賂議會，來駁回激進的改革
and lobby the congress to kill big reform
然後再把鍋甩到移民和窮鬼身上
and then they blamed immigrants and poor people
這次，連教師也跟著被指責
and this time even teachers!
這些都說完做完以後，只有一個銀行家被關了監獄
And when all was said and done, only one single banker went to jail
這個倒霉蛋！
This poor schmuck!
瑞士瑞信銀行的卡里姆
Kareem Serageldin from Credit Suisse
他在房貸證券中損失了幾十億
He hit a few billion in mortgage-bond losses
但對金融危機的大銀行來說 這些損失都是平常事兒
Something most of the big banks did on a good day during the crisis
馬克，我們能出手了嗎
Mark, can we sell now?
現在基金能回收10億
I mean the fund will almost make a billion dollars
你能清算出2億來
You'll clear two-hundred mill Mark!
可是…如果我們出手
You know... once we sell..
最終和他們又有什麼不一樣
We'll be just like the rest of them
你知道我的意思
You know that!
不一樣，我們不是壞人
No we're not, we're not the bad guys here!
我們沒有利用美國人 想要有個房子的夢想來詐騙
we didn't defraud the American people and prey on their dreams of owning a home
像他們那樣
Like they did!
現在出手能打得他們找牙
Now we get to kick em in the teeth!
10億美元
a billion dollars
是的
That's right!
但是我們必須盡快平倉 否則可能拿不回錢了
But we gotta close out our position, or it could be zero
機不可失，時不再來，馬克
I- I- It's now or never, Mark
好吧
Okay.
全賣出去！
Sell it all!
* 等金融動盪塵埃落定
*When the dust settled form the collapse
* 總共有5萬億美元消失不見 包括養老金，房地產…
*5 trillion dollars in pension money, real estate value
* …401K退休福利，存款和證券。
*401k, savings, and bonds had disappeared.
*8百萬人失業，6百萬人無家可歸
*8 million people lost their jobs,6 million lost their homes.
*這還只是美國的情況
*And that was just in the USA.
*馬克·鮑姆的妻子，辛西婭說
*Mark Baum's wife, Cynthia, says mark actually
*馬克在金融危機之後變得謙和了
*became gracious after the collapse and
* 再也不對人說“我早就告訴過你”了
*never said "I told you so" to anyone
*他的手下丹尼、文尼和伯特…
*Danny,Vinny and Porter all still
*還在曼哈頓經營一家基金
*run a fund together in Manhattan...
*公司旁邊就有松久壽司店
*...where there is a Nobu.
*查理和傑米試圖去…
*Charlie Geller and Jamie Shipley attempted
*起訴信用評級機構
*to sue the ratings agencies
*所有的律所都嘲笑他們太天真
*but were laughed out of all law offices.
*傑米還在經營棕地基金
*Jamie still runs Brownfield
*但是查理離開了紐約
*but Charlie left New York
*在北卡羅來納州的夏洛特安家立業
* to live in Charlotte and start a family
*本現在和妻子有一個大果園自給自足
*Ben Rickert now lives with his wife on a large orchard.
*他們保存了很多種子
* They have plenty of seeds.
*麥克·貝利，幾次去聯繫政府
*Michael Burry contacted the government serveral times
*看看是否有人願意採訪他
*to see if anyone wanted to interview him
*去了解他對金融系統的看法
*to find out how he know the system
*為什麼只有他提前預測到了金融危機
*would collapse years before anyone else.
*但從沒有人回過他電話
*No one ever returned his calls.
*可是他本人被審訊過4次
*But he was audited four times
*被聯邦調查局查賬
*and questioned by the FBI.
*他現在唯一在做的小型投資
*The small investing he still does
*只關注一種商品：
*is all focused on one commodity:
*淡水
*water
*2015年開始，很多的大銀行發售十億規模的
*In 2015, several large banks began selling billions
*“定制分級機會投資”
*in something called a "bespoke tranche opportunity."
*據彭博新聞的分析
* Which,acoording to Bloomberg News
*這就是CDO改了個名字
*is just another name for a CDO.
《大空頭》
*THE BIG SHORT
bgm 《When The Levee Breaks》by Led Zeppelin
*bgm: When The Levee Breaks, by Led Zeppelin
根據麥克·劉易斯同名書籍改編
*Based upon the book by Michael Lewis
* 你買的理財產品 公司債券
* notice
* 評級真的都是AAA級嗎？
本電影由 悠悠電影 原創壓製
www.YoYozz.com